<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><events xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<day>All Weekend</day>
<event><title>Chaos Machine</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> This customizable marble roller coaster is a perennial favorite, serving as a metaphor for the open source development process. The Chaos Machine is available all weekend for Penguicon attendees to tinker with! <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Free Fates Fortune Telling Booth</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Valerie Hibbard</participant> Find a token, bring it to the booth in the lobby, and randomly generated predictions will be given to you! You may also write a short question and receive a Yes or No answer in return. Hours of operation posted at the booth. <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Giant Jenga</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Stop by and play some (enormous) Jenga with your friends, or meet new people. No writing dirty things on the blocks! You'll just have to use your imagination. <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>NUET Scouts</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Justin Coluzzi, Kevin McLeod, Alex Drummer</participant> The Scouts are at it again! The Nearly Useless Entertainment Team is back for another year at Penguicon, bringing you fun, mayhem, and shenanigans. Find us wandering the con to see what we have planned this year. <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Pengicon Picture Bingo</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Snap a picture of each clue and you will be rewarded! Go to Registration, Ops, or the Greeter Table to get started! <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Pirate Sea Chanties!</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate</participant> Rathbone the Pirate will enchant us with authentic sea chanties throughout the weekend! <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Ribbon Fairies</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Look out for the Ribbon Fairies! If you find them, you can trade them a ribbon for a ribbon! <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Where in the World?</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Wondering where people are coming from to go to Penguicon?  Stop by and tag the city you came from on the World, US or Michigan map! <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Pirate Treasure Hunt!</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Mystery Location</room>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate</participant> Temporary description <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Artemis</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>321</room>
<blurb><participant>Lansing Maker Network</participant> Welcome to the L.M.N. Artemis, Lansing Makers Network’s very own Starship Bridge simulator </blurb></event>
<event><title>Dangeous Things</title>
<topic>Tech, Life, DIY</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Amal Graafstra, Anita Fowler</participant> Featured Guests Dangerous Things will be set up in our Hacker Space throughout the weekend offering RFID implantation services. Please stop by and talk to them for more information and for costs. <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<day>FRIDAY, APRIL 29</day>
<time>4 PM</time>
<event><title>I know Kung Fu</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike SanDiego</participant> " I know Kung Fu." Sound familiar? Thanks to movies like the Matrix and Kung Fu Panda, this ancient martial art is fairly well known in the west. But do you actually know what it really is? If you want to find out, come and learn some basics of this ancient art form that is thousands of years old, and get a taste of what real Kung fu is like!  This workshop will be active, so dress comfortably! Workout pants and sneakers would be ideal, dress clothes, costumes, or restrictive clothing should be avoided. For safety reasons, this is not a workshop generally recommended for children or those with medical and or physical conditions that would make high mobility a health risk. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>LN2 Welcome Back Ice Cream</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room>Consuite</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Elkins, Phil Salkie</participant> For the opening session of Liquid Nitrogen Ice Cream, we tell you the ingredients on hand and we make fun and tasty flavors together.  Alternative ingredients available; we can make some non-dairy or sugar-free! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>5 PM</time>
<event><title>Editors, Publishers, and Readers-- What Rules to Break and Which Don't Apply</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Leckie, Michael K. Elliot, Steven Saus, Tobias Buckell, Stacy Bender</participant> Many new authors have heard the rules: One POV per scene, don't use adverbs, Limit the POVs to no more than three per story. These "rules" have been taught for over a hundred years, but who came up with them and do they still apply to the modern reader? </blurb></event>
<event><title>SAR Lessons</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Susan Sons</participant> Have you ever considered volunteering as an emergency responder, or are you simply curious about what happens in disaster areas when the "official" help runs out?  An experienced former search and rescue (SAR) volunteer will share lessons learned about SAR operations, and perhaps a little about life. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Basic Skills for Working with Electronics</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Christopher Bright</participant> This presentation will cover the very very basics of DC circuit theory and the skills needed to cut and prep wire and then solder it together or to a component. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Time Management</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Hannah Davis</participant> How to work, enjoy your hobbies, and still sleep. </blurb></event>
<event><title>How To Be Civilized Online</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Mitchell Bowling, John Belden</participant> The internet allows us to express our opinions, good and bad, anonymously and instantaneously.  Learn how to be a better cyber-citizen. </blurb></event>
<event><title>So This Is Your First Penguicon</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Kennedy</participant> Our chair, Scott, will talk about why Penguicon is an awesome con and community, and give you a tour of what's in store for you this weekend.  If you're new to Penguicon and you want to get to know the event, this is the panel for you! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Why Webcomics?</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>BluRaven C. Houvener</participant> The internet is such a vital part of our day to day lives that even books have taken the digital plunge and comics have leapt from the page to the tablet screen. Come find out what makes a Webcomic a Webcomic and why you should be reading them if you aren't already. </blurb></event>
<time>6 PM</time>
<event><title>Whose Geek Are You Anyway?</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Derek Newland</participant> Come join in some geeky "Whose Line Is It Anyway" style hijinks!  PG-13 content to be expected, fun for everyone!  Get ready to laugh and have ideas of things you'd like to do, or see others do! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Opening Ceremonies</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Kennedy, Daniel Dugan, Nuri Gocay, Cylithria Dubois, Amanda Long-Adams, Amanda Robinson, Miranda Webster, Jessica Roland, Julie, Winningham, Ann Lemay, Ann Leckie, Cathrynne Valente, Deb Nicholson, Jason Mars, Lingjia Tang</participant> Join our con chair, Scott Kennedy, the Con Committee, and our Guests of Honor as we open this bad boy up for the weekend.  You never know what surprises might be in store! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Getting Hands on With Linux</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Lawrence</participant> Who put the penguin in Penguicon? You did! Come get hands on with Linux with one of our favorite presenters. Tom Lawrence will guide attendees through the ins and outs of Linux for home and office use. Noteworthy addendum! There will be 20 laptops available in the lab. First come, first served. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Loving Your Cosplay Body</title>
<topic>Costuming</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson, John Belden</participant> Just because you are not an exact replica of the character you'd like to be doesn't mean you can't pull off a great cosplay of them. Size, sex, race, or physical abilities should not hold you back from being who you really want to be. We will discuss how to accept, cover, camouflage, and overcome your body issues and cosplay with confidence. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Basic Sewing: Make a pillow</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>RainbowRavenX</participant> Whether you have never even seen a needle and thread, or have been sewing since you were three, come join me as I teach the basics. In this hands-on activity we will create and embellish a pillow. I will teach how to attach buttons, appliqués, ribbon and decorative trim. I will also teach how to do a basic hand stitch as well as a decorative blanket stitch.  The end result will be a decorative pillow for you to take home.  No experience necessary. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Social Media for Writers</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>David Erik Nelson, Andrea Johnson, Michael W. Lucas, Christopher Purrett, Alex Kourvo</participant> What social media trends does a writer building their web footprint need to understand? What are some Dos and Don'ts? </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Art of Retro Gamers</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Ian Sterrett, Bob Waltenspiel, Jeremy Myers, Dave Phillips</participant> Journey to a panel in time discussing how fun it was to play games like Super Mario, Duck Hunt , Battle Toads and Dragon Warrior...losing your friends over frustration, gaining strong bonds by defeating tough bosses and networking as compared to now... </blurb></event>
<event><title>How Not To Draw Comics</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>BluRaven C. Houvener, Noa Page, Jon David</participant> This is a judgment free zone...but have you ever looked at a comic and thought, “Wow that doesn't look right”. You've come to the right place. We'll study the comic greats and have a laugh as we explore the made up muscle groups, humanly impossible poses, and just downright ponder how it made it from the drawing table to the rack at your local comic book store! </blurb></event>
<time>7 PM</time>
<event><title>Open Source Martial Arts</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Kent Newland</participant> There are a great many martial artists here at Penguicon!  Come on down and work on some problem solving together!  Learn about the similarities and differences between European, Chinese, Japanese, Filipino, Indonesian, Malaysian, and all other martial arts styles!  Traditional, non-traditional, all are welcome here! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>All Hands Active Keynote</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Greg Gage</participant> Have you ever been curious about how your five senses really sense? How can you remember what your grandmother looks like? The secret lies in your body’s hidden electrical network that lives just below our skin and skulls: our nervous system! This talk will be hands-on demonstration of the basic principles of neuroscience and will explore the fascinating field of “electrophysiology”. Using our "DIY" neuroscience tools, we will begin to see and hear what the brain actually looks like! We will continue to go deeper… exploring neurophysiology, functional electrical stimulation, micro-stimulation’s effect on animal behavior, neuropharmacology, even neuroprosthesis and human-to-human interfaces! (Don’t worry… all these will be explained in easy-to-follow experiments). </blurb></event>
<event><title>Writing Group 101</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Christian Klaver, David Erik Nelson, Cindy Spencer Pape</participant> How to Survive and Thrive in a Writing Group </blurb></event>
<event><title>Microprocessor Magic</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Christopher Bright</participant> Add movement, color, sound, and interactivity with a tiny computer system designed for artists and designers. Christopher Bright shows us how to use the Arduino microcontroller to take in information and then express it through lights, sounds, or motion. The potential here is limitless. Arduinos have been used to build opensource EEG machines, heart rate monitors, robotic motion controllers. In this workshop you will create a heart-rate sensor that in turn flashes an LED on time. Easy, and very fun. I will have plenty of micro boards on hand for folks to play with and a selection of kits for sale at dramatically reduced prices compared to retail. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Writing Software For Penguicon</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Matt Arnold</participant> Convention Resource Event Management (CREM) is an open-source web app. It catches conflicts between rooms, times, and presenters. It is flexible enough to track the necessary data about everything from LN2 Ice Cream to board games, and prevent a loud concert from being on the other side of an airwall from a quiet panel discussion. Get involved, or just satisfy your curiosity about the languages and frameworks: Javascript with Angular, and Python with Flask. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Staying Fit On The Go</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>William E. Bowen</participant> Join us on a discussion about different ways to stay healthy and active no matter where you are. Topics will also include things you can do right now during the convention. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Comic vs. Manga</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> This panel highlights the differences and similarities between Comics and Anime, including everything from the influences of each to crossovers and general themes. Audience participation is encouraged! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Social Skills in a Digital Age</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Mitch "Duckman" Peters, Jennifer Resibig, Katherine Hatfield Nix</participant> Flirting, dating, making friends, influencing people, even simple conversation, all of these things tend to get harder in real life, even as our online inter-connectedness increases! We're here to talk about simple, fun and easy ways to help your IRL social interactions be more LOL and less STFU. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Frankenstuffies</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>RainbowRavenX</participant> Come join me in playing "mad scientist" as we deconstruct stuffed animals, and reconstruct them into new and glorious creations!  Everyone is welcome, though I do ask that parents/guardians stay with children. Basic sewing skills are a plus. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Demos by BeagleBone, DangerousThings and AHA</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Live demos and highlights for of this weekends events as the Penguicon Hackerspace spins up for the weekend! <duration>3 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Editing for Your Spouse/Partner/BFF/Pet</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Favre, Clif Flynt, Janice Leach, Jim Leach</participant> "Can you read this and tell me what you think?" is a question to test any relationship.  We will learn some ways to navigate that communications mine-field while musing on the nature of editing, the care and feeding of your larval writer and some small, practical steps towards upping our editing game. </blurb></event>
<event><title>When Being 'On' is What People Expect</title>
<topic>Media, Life</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Tanya DePass, Mark Oshiro</participant> A panel where Mark Oshiro (Mark Does Stuff) and Tanya DePass (I Need Diverse Games) speak about the performative aspects of their work, including the need to entertain while doing blind reads and reactions to media and for Tanya; while streaming on Twitch/YT Gaming. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Comics in the Classroom</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Noa Page</participant> With visual culture becoming more and more integral to our lives, teachers are turning to comics as a new source for pedagogical material. This panel discusses strategies for integrating comics into elementary, high school and university teaching. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Improving Leadership with IT</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Dr. Justin Coven</participant> Exceptional leadership is the ability to methodically and continually create heroes!   From an organizational perspective, most leadership research and theory is focused around individual leader psychology. IT Maturity takes an alternative IT perspective of leaders as entities operating within organizations, orchestrating how other entities interact with each other, to optimize productivity.  IT Maturity Leadership includes principles in five different categories: Management, Organization (structure), Extent (of activities), Culture, and Vision.  IT tools can be used to help enterprises to do this both technically and organizationally (i.e. enable individuals to excel). </blurb></event>
<event><title>Kerbal Space Program</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Bob Trembley</participant> Kerbal Space Program (KSP) has taken computer gaming and brought it crashing into the realm of a true space simulator. In KSP, you build rockets, launch them, get them into space, do SCIENCE! there, build space stations and moon bases... do SCIENCE! there, and travel to other worlds... and do more SCIENCE!  Kerbal Space Program is like being a kid in a candy store the size of the solar system! </blurb></event>
<time>8 PM</time>
<event><title>Financial Planning</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Ericka S. Kahler</participant> As much as we might want to avoid it, we're slowing becoming adults with adult responsibilites.  We can all use advice on money management and planning for our future. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Comics and the Movies Review!</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Lady Ana, Professor X</participant> It’s that time of the year again where we get together with Lady Ana and Professor X and talk the talk about comic books and their impact on the movies, television, and life in general.  We’ll talk about Batman v Superman Marvel’s Civil War, Dr. Strange, The Infinity War with the Avengers, The Age of Apocalypse with the X-Men, and the fate of the Fantastic Four. We’ll also talk about the explosion of Marvel and DC characters on television.  There will be door prizes, free comics, and as always, we will have the Mjolnir available for those who speak in the name of the awesomeness of the comics world. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Friendship at the Speed of Sound</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Jessica Roland</participant> This is a speed friending event where participants will pair up and get to know one another with the hopes of finding a Con Buddy.  We'll have questions to keep the conversation going! </blurb></event>
<event><title>So You Want to Write Video Games?</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Lemay, John Scalzi</participant> Guest of Honor Ann Lemay and John Scalzi talk about what goes into writing the narrative stories for videogames. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Linux Computer Lab (Unconference)</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>No Presenter</participant> Open Computer lab utilizing the Unconference philosophy of Open Space Technology. Bring your projects to discuss. Bring your discussions to projects. Attendees may also peruse social media, tweet to #Penguicon, browse the whole internet and get a feel for Linux using one of our 20 laptops. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Real-World Pandemic and Deliberate Extinctions: Ending Polio and Guinea Worm</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Jennifer Hamilton</participant> Thanks to sustained public-health measures and health advocates willing to risk their lives, humanity is on the verge of winning two real-world games of Pandemic.  Polio, which once paralyzed 1000 children around the world every day, is now endemic only in two countries.  Guinea worm, a 80-cm long parasite associated with stagnant water, has gone from 3.5 million cases annually in the mid-1980s to only 22 cases in 2015. Jennifer Hamilton MD will talk about the human suffering associated with these diseases, the ongoing efforts to eradicate them, and policies that help support reduction of infectious diseases in general. </blurb></event>
<event><title>LGBTQ* Alphabet Soup</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Cassy Sinke, Alison Chan, April Nance</participant> An educational take on the different terms used within the LGBTQ* community. We'll start from basic terms and work our way through some not so common terms. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Firearms and Law</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Richard Houser</participant> Join your Firearms and the Law panelists for a discussion of all things firearms related:  law, training practices, depictions in media, gun control, background checks, holster preferences, favorite ammo, reloading, etc. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Influence of Anime in Media</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Fans of anime and manga know it's influenced our lives, but what about the other kinds of media we consume? Television, music, and games draw more and more inspiration from anime every day, and not always in obvious ways. </blurb></event>
<event><title>So Fresh, (Not) So Clean; Getting Dirty Making Soap.</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>FOOD</room>
<blurb><participant>Jonathan Ivar Weyhrauch, Mikhail Shikhmanov</participant> Reroot, a local producer of all natural hand made soaps and oils, will demonstrate one of the processes they use to make soap. We will touch on how to formulate a soap with the properties you desire and the chemical reactions that turn oils into soap. Come join us in getting dirty to make others clean. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Dealing with the Paranormal</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Shetan Noir</participant> Come and learn how to remove unwanted things/beings from your life, home and being.  This presentation will include discussion of different practices and spells and ingredients that help to remove paranormal annoyances.  After ghost hunting and magically cleansing many homes, I have found different things that work to remove attachments and parasitic paranormals. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Star Trek Five-Year Mission With Mini Expansions</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>David Whitcher</participant> Dice. The Final Frontier. Voyage to explore strange new expansions-- to seek out new victory points and new challenges-- to meet the game's designer-- to boldly go where no players have gone before! A cooperative dice placement game. Take roles from original or Next Gen. Players try to cooperatively solve a series of alerts to score points, without failing five alerts, or the Enterprise being destroyed. Injuries lock dice out of play. Ship damage forces you to attempt harder alerts. Urgent events must be completed on a timer (the Prime Directive). Yellow &amp; red alerts force additional alerts cards to come into play-- pushing you and your fellow crew-members closer to failing! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Star Trek Five-Year Mission With Mini Expansions</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>David Whitcher</participant> Dice. The Final Frontier. Voyage to explore strange new expansions-- to seek out new victory points and new challenges-- to meet the game's designer-- to boldly go where no players have gone before! A cooperative dice placement game. Take roles from original or Next Gen. Players try to cooperatively solve a series of alerts to score points, without failing five alerts, or the Enterprise being destroyed. Injuries lock dice out of play. Ship damage forces you to attempt harder alerts. Urgent events must be completed on a timer (the Prime Directive). Yellow &amp; red alerts force additional alerts cards to come into play-- pushing you and your fellow crew-members closer to failing! </blurb></event>
<event><title>PAM: You're Doing It Wrong</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas</participant> PAM, or Pluggable Authentication Modules, is one of the most occult parts of managing Unixish systems. The unique configuration syntax and idiosyncratic rule processing drives many sysadmins to copy working configurations from other people and random blog posts. This talk takes you through the essentials of PAM configuration, You'll learn the components of PAM, how PAM processes rules, how to use multi-factor authentication, and get an overview of some useful PAM modules you probably haven't used, based on my book "PAM Mastery." </blurb></event>
<time>9 PM</time>
<event><title>Wesley and the Crushers</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Wesley and the Crushers is a modern, one-of-a-kind musical exploration that is both "geeky" and passionate -- passionate in their admiration and love for all things "geeky" -- and completely geeked-out in their approach to their number-one passion, which is music. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Ethics of Raising Children While Participating in the BDSM Community</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>RainbowRavenX</participant> So you're into kink, and then one day have kids. Those kids start growing up, they stumble upon your toy bag or notice that bruise that you got last night, and they start asking questions. What do you do? Do you make up a story? Tell them the truth? Bribe them with ice cream and toys to never speak of this again? Whether you live it 24/7 or only play on the weekends, are a sub or a Dom, a little, a pet player, or practitioner of any other kink, come join me for a round table discussion about all the challenges of raising children while being part of the BDSM community. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Big Data Tools</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael Grube</participant> We'll cover the free, open source tools required to create an automated analytics pipeline for whatever data you may be interested in. Specifically, we'll talk about ETL and Analysis with Spark, Hadoop as a data store, and Relational databases.  Students will be provided an example pipeline as well as a fully configured VM to play with. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Queer Poly Speed Dating</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Nicole Rohr</participant> Come join us for a speed dating event especially for queer poly people! <duration>1 hour and 30 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Rope Basics: The Bedroom &amp; Beyond</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>kernelbrandon</participant> This is a hands-on rope workshop that will quickly teach basic rope skills for the bedroom. Learn safe ways to tie someone to a bed or restrict their movement. A limited amount of rope will be available for loan. </blurb></event>
<event><title>History in Speculative Fiction (and Other Literature)</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Clif Flynt, Steven Saus, Nicole Castle, Robert Kroese</participant> The historical details can bring a story to life or bog it down. What's the right balance? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Sleeping on the Job: Why (and How) to Catch That Daytime Nap</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Marie Staver</participant> In just 20 minutes, a nap can make us happier, more energetic and more focused -- so why is it so hard to get one at work, even at an office job? Long-term tech worker and polyphasic sleeper Marie explores the pros and cons, the surprising politics, and the nitty-gritty how-to of getting a nap during your daily grind. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Poetry Starter Kit</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Jim Leach, Sean Davis</participant> Audience Participation Panel: Speculative Poetry Starter Kit: who to read, where to look and exactly what the heck IS speculative poetry. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Anatomy of a Sewing Machine</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Bagel Garrison</participant> Have a sewing machine, but have no idea how to activate the magic that powers it? Don't have a sewing machine, but are thinking about getting one? This panel will be an absolute from-the-ground-up explanation of how to use, set up, and care for a sewing machine. Bring your own if you'd like, for a more personalized explanation. If time allows, you can do a test-sew on one of my machines, or I'll help you with your own. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BDSM: An Introduction to Kink</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>(Rabbit) Michael McPeek</participant> Handcuffs - Riding crops - Whips - Chains. Does some of this excite you?  Curious about BDSM? Then come join us for a short introductory class where you'll learn about different, simple types of play to get you started. Easy things to try tonight! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Dark Web Big Three</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Portage Auditorium</room>
<blurb><participant>Pat Baker</participant> Get and introduction to the big three in censorship-resistant communication, TOR, I2P and freenet and learn how they work and some of the options they have available. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Social Hour</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Restaurant</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Get to know our Guests of Honor and Featured Guests as we all get together for some cocktails. Meet us in the bar! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Eric S. Raymond "Ask Me Anything!"</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Eric S. Raymond</participant> Eric S. Raymond answers your questions about anything! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Easy and Cheap: Healthy Meatless Meals</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Amy Alice Wright</participant> Get your grub on with some fast, nutritious meals that won't make your wallet sad. We're talking tasty stews, soups, curries, and sides with minimum prep and cooking time. We'll demo a hearty main course and side that you can taste at the end of the session. Recipes will be provided, plus some others to try, and we'll give you a resource sheet to find lots of other cheap and easy vegan vittles! </blurb></event>
<time>10 PM</time>
<event><title>Impact Play for Beginners</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>(Rabbit) Michael McPeek</participant> Want to learn about impact play? Then come in and play!  This interactive class, geared toward beginners, will show you how to get started doing impact play with floggers and riding crops. You'll learn where and where not to hit, how to practice, and different types of impact toys - some found even right in your kitchen! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Primal: Understanding Yourself &amp; Your Role in the Kink Community</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>George Allen</participant> An informational talk for those who identify as primal or who wish to learn more about what it is and how it impacts the BDSM community. Come learn about primals, share information about primal scenes, and learn techniques to manage the inner animal. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Flirting for Geeks</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Nuri Gocay, Bob Waltenspiel, Dave Phillips, Scott Kennedy, Marie Staver</participant> Come learn how (and how not) to flirt from some of our local fandom's biggest flirts. Not only is it laugh-out-loud funny, it's an irreverent and honest reflection of love, sex, and fandom. Find ways to woo, methods for making friends, and how to have a good time without making others uncomfortable. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Live Podcast: Getting Drunk with Shannon &amp; Maggie</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Shannon Marshall, Maggie Maiville</participant> Shannon and Maggie are BFF’s and they (used to) drink, a lot. Join us for our 3rd time at Penguicon. Hilarity will ensue, we will drink, eat cheese, and discuss the latest events in life and entertainment. Audience members will be able to submit questions to be answered live during the session directly, during the recording, to Shannon and Maggie or via Twitter at @ShannonsParty and @BrainOfMaggie </blurb></event>
<event><title>DemonLobster.com presents: Sanity Claws Radio Live</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Jonathon Hickey, Scott Markwart</participant> The Demon Lobster crew invites you to this live recording of our podcast, "Sanity Claws Radio". The crew will be playing an audience driven game of "I Can Top That" where you get to ask our panel questions about games, movies, or anything in nerd culture and we quest to give the funniest answer possible. Raunchy humor and adult language abound in this panel. As a result, this panel is for (im)mature audiences only. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Music Parody Performance: Derwood Bowen</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Derwood Bowen</participant> Derwood Bowen is a multi-genre comedy artist from the suburbs of Columbus, OH, and his live show comes with fun songs, lots of props, occasional attire changes, and audience involvement.  If you're in need of a good laugh, this is the place to go for it! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Ubuntu Michigan 16.04 Release Party</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Restaurant</room>
<blurb><participant>Craig Maloney</participant> Come celebrate the release of Ubuntu 16.04: Xenial Xerus with the Ubuntu Michigan Loco. We'll be meeting in the bar area to celebrate the latest in the Ubuntu release cycle. Hope to see you there! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The ZFS File System</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas</participant> ZFS, the Zettabyte File System, is one of the most full-featured filesystems available today and gives almost unlimited storage flexibility. Originally created by Sun Microsystems, the independent entity OpenZFS now develops ZFS as deployed in illumos, Linux, and FreeBSD.  This talk takes you through ZFS' features, including: data self-healing, deduplication and compression, clones and snapshots, copy-on-write, boot environments, replication, and more. Once you use ZFS, you'll never understand how you lived without it. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Midwest Mash - Whiskies of the Great Lakes</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<blurb><participant>Greg Williams</participant> There are a significant number of craft distilleries in the Midwest region, come and hear what makes them unique from each other, how those whiskies are made. Then stay for a tasting!  The presentation will be open, but the tasting will be limited participation. 21+ and ID will be required. Sign up at Ops. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Poly Speed Dating</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Nicole Rohr</participant> Polyamory speed dating will help polamorous people of all types get to know each other! <duration>25 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>11 PM</time>
<event><title>Rope for Decoration and Restraint</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>kernelbrandon</participant> Learn the ins and outs of a few basic harnesses and how to integrate more decorative knotwork into your rope ties. There will be some discussion of flow in a rope scene. A limited amount of rope will be available for loan. </blurb></event>
<event><title>LN2 After Hours I Ice Cream</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room>Consuite</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Elkins, Phil Salkie</participant> Some ice creams / sorbets may be made with alcohol for this event.  Only legal drinking age attendees allowed.  IDs will be checked. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<day>SATURDAY, APRIL 30</day>
<time>8 AM</time>
<event><title>JAC3D G33K Fitness Bootcamp</title>
<topic>Life, Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>William E. Bowen</participant> A heart pumping, high adrenaline full body training experience designed to trim and sculpt you for the hot months a head.  Includes strength training using various options including body weight, resistance bands to the keep the body guessing along with cardio intervals to maximize calories burned.  This training session will also be accompanied by some of the greatest video game and nerd core music. </blurb></event>
<time>9 AM</time>
<event><title>Open Linux Computer Lab (Unconference)</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>No Presenter</participant> Open Computer lab utilizing the Unconference philosophy of Open Space Technology. Bring your projects to discuss. Bring your discussions to projects. Attendees may also peruse social media, tweet to #Penguicon, browse the whole internet and get a feel for Linux using one of our 20 laptops. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Soldering and Embedded Programming with All Hands Active</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Get Hands-on with a Penguicon Tradition. All Hands Active members will have kits for sale to solder and program the latest iteration of their Penguicon upgraded badges. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Coffee, The Other Java</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Kelly Vanderwell</participant> Learn the differences in coffee drinks: cappucino, frappe, latte, americano, espresso, etc so you can confidently order drinks at even the fanciest coffee shops. </blurb></event>
<time>10 AM</time>
<event><title>Geeks with Guns Virtual Range</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Stuart Chisholm, Rob Reed</participant> Love to shoot handguns but can't make it to our live fire event before the con?  Or want to learn how to shoot but without the noise, recoil and potential danger?  OR just want to have a great time?  Then the Virtual Range is a must visit!  The only things flying downrange are photons.  Our Laser pistols have the look and feel of a real Glock 17, but emit only light.  Newbies will get actual instruction from certified professionals free of charge!  This time out, we have added more reactive targets to the mix -- things that jump, fall or light up – for even more fun!  Get your "Geek Militia" ribbon ONLY at the GwG Virtual Range! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>TopicHero  for Topic Heroes</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Dr. Justin Coven</participant> TopicHero (http://TopicHero.com) allows users to create and share multiple Topics across different devices and browsers. Topic elements include Search Engines, RSS Feeds, and Links, in addition to typical web page elements. This is a different way of slicing web information, where the focus is on Topics as opposed to a focus on a Search Engine, device, browser, or RSS Feed. TopicHero arises from a philosophy that it is the topic that is critical and that users need effective tools to bring as many resources to bare on specific topics as possible. This is particularly true in business where many users are dedicated to working on specific topics for long periods of time. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Manager or Leader? Running a Technical Team</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Jer Lance, Dawn Kuczwara</participant> Are you currently supervising a technical team? Maybe you're considering taking the plunge? Come hear a few voices "from the trenches" talk about what it's really like to lead a team: the good, the bad, the horrible, and the horribly funny. Topics will include: the differences between a manager and a leader, leading from the front, why your manager isn't out to get you, managing up, ethical communication, and more </blurb></event>
<event><title>Networking for Awkward People</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Chioke Mose-Telesford, Kim Driscoll</participant> Ever find yourself at a networking event, unable to think of how to introduce yourself to the people around you? As sweat pours down your face, do you say, "Hi, my name is Annalisa," and then just blank? We've got you covered. You'll walk out with a full-proof "elevator pitch" and tactics to conquer any nerves, small talk or curveballs. Be warned - you'll actually be up and moving and trying this out on your fellow attendees. And make eye contact. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Navigation strategies for a Career in IT</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Donald Mark Haynes, Douglas Johnson</participant> Interested in strategies for navigating a career in IT, or finding out how you break into IT in the first place? How do you transition to the next job?  How do you market yourself? How do you determine if your current skills are marketable? The panelists will discuss various topics and provide real life examples. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Python for Everything and Everybody</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Gibson Nichols, Daniel Dugan</participant> Join MDLUG and friends to walk through an introductory course on building small useful scripts in Python. Get your hands dirty in the fertile soil that is sprouting some of the most interesting developments in machine learning, server scripting and automation! Noteworthy addendum! There will be 20 laptops available in the lab. First come, first served. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>How to Poison Your Muse: The Toxic Twins of Talent and Art</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Paul Kemner, Michael Cieslak</participant> We'll discuss how common ideas about talent and art sabotage our creativity. What are these traps, and how can we avoid them? A discussion for artists, authors, musicians, and anyone else who wants to create good stuff. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Cosplay 101</title>
<topic>Costuming</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson, John Belden</participant> Dressing up really seems like fun. You've seen other people doing it and now you think you might want to try it yourself. I can provide you with some advice, tips, and tricks in order to get you on the right track. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Build Your Own Satellite!</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Scheraga, Paul Frick</participant> The i3Detroit Makerspace has started the design process to build what is likely the first Makerspace-based CubeSat-sized satellite. We will discuss its development so far, design considerations and steps going forward. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Webcomics 101-Self Promotion</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Erika Wagner, Laura Cascos</participant> So you've learned from parts 1 and 2 how to make your Webcomic, how to build up the world around your characters and follow it all to completion. What now? You stand alone with your work. It's awesome. The world needs to bask in its awesomeness! What's that? How do you get it to them, you ask? Great question, and here is your answer! Come join Erika Wagner and Laura Cascos for part 3 of 3 of Webcomics 101! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Backyard Brains Demo #1</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Greg Gage</participant> Neuroscientist and engineer Greg Gage will demonstrate the SpikerBox -- a small rig that helps kids understand the electrical impulses that control the nervous system. He's passionate about helping everyone understand (viscerally) how our brains and our neurons work. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Dangerous Things Does Implanations</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Amal Graafstra, Anita Fowler</participant> Yes, we are turning people into cyborgs. Expect a demonstration of really awesome technology that can help you unlock your doors, phone, make electronic payments, contain your medical information, and all kinds of other fun stuff.  Join Dangerous Things as they implants RFIDs into anyone who wants them in a safe and sterile manner! Please stop by the HackerSpace to ask about costs! <duration>12 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Needle Felting</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Bagel Garrison</participant> Needle Felting! You get to stab things! In this panel, we'll needle-felt a simple flat penguin, suitable for making into pendant/pin/whatever. Materials will be provided. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to OpenBSD</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>STeve Andre', Marcus Watts</participant> OpenBSD is a variety of Unix that is similar to Linux, but with perhaps a stronger security focus. It is a project run by volunteers, and is a free software program. Come and learn more about this alternative operating system. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Zenoss</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Andrew D Kirch</participant> An Introduction to Network Monitoring utilizing the Open Source Zenoss Monitoring System.  Topics covered will include configuration, managing monitored hosts via SNMP, SSH, and basic remediation. </blurb></event>
<event><title>LSDj n' U! A How-To Track and Perform Live with Chiptunes!</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Jacob Dean McGranaghan, Corey Chappell, Garrett Boone</participant> Have you ever been curious to know how chip artists compose music on a classic Nintendo Gameboy? Or even been more curious on how they tweak their tunes during a live performance? Snesei, Dollfin, and McGRANAMAN will not only show you the basics of LSDj and various tips and tricks of the program, but they'll also give insights on how to manipulate the pre-tracked song for live performances. At the end, audience members are invited to try LSDj's LIVE mode to create their own, unique Gameboy tune. </blurb></event>
<event><title>First Things First: Story Titles </title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Jon David, Alex Kourvo, Christine Daigle, Michael Cieslak</participant> First Things First: Story Titles: Which comes first, a story or its title? What makes a good title? Who gets to decide what that title would be? Should a title hint at the story to come, or only make sense after the story is read?  </blurb></event>
<time>11 AM</time>
<event><title>The Future of Biohacking</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Amal Graafstra, Anita Fowler, Greg Gage</participant> Three of our Featured Guests look into the future to discuss how we could incorporate new technology into our bodies, and what the benefits can be for us as individuals and as communities. </blurb></event>
<event><title>What Have You Read?</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Jim Leach, Andrea Johnson, Stewart Sternberg, Nicole Castle</participant> What's something amazing that you read recently that you want to tell the world about? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Overthrow the Trichromatocracy: Making Color-blind Friendly UIs</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Favre</participant> Think your snazzy new UI is fantastic? Did you test it with color-blind users? No? Then you're probably in for a surprise for how much information you are trying to convey in a way that is not accessible to your users who have colorblindness or color sight deficiencies. We will discuss the details of what it means to be color blind and what you can do as a programmer or designer to improve the usability of your software for the 1 in 12 of your users who are color blind. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Fedora Roadmap</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Callaway</participant> Take a look at one of the premiere Linux distributions which serves as the testing ground for Red Hat Linux. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Podcasting</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Dave Phillips, Bob Waltenspiel, Nuri Gocay, Karen Hubbard, Shannon Marshall, Maggie Maiville, Jonathan Hickey, Scott Markwart</participant> All the cool kids are doing it...and more importantly, even more of the not so cool kids are doing it - podcasting. So what do you need to know to get started? Go live or record and syndicate only? What kind of mics? What should you know before getting started? In your basement or a studio somewhere? Learn from local podcasters with lots of experience and known throughout the podcasting community. </blurb></event>
<event><title>ScreenWriting Tips</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>James Fernandez, Mary Lynn Gibbs, Dave Kilgore</participant> Aching to write a script for that great movie idea that's been bouncing around in your head? Come get some tips and tricks for how to get started on writing a script. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>The Pre-Production Process for Films - Where It All Comes Together:</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike Madigan, Matthew Peach</participant> Learn more about the screenwriting process and getting your short or feature film ready for production, as well as the pre-production elements of casting, securing locations, choosing the right gear for your production, and getting your production team together. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Deployment and Testing</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Mark Henke</participant> Come share your experiences in deploying and testing software.  Birds of a Feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Silicone Casting for Cheap Bastards</title>
<topic>Costuming</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Gnora Ford-Lepthien</participant> Ever wanted to make things out of silicone but don't want to spend a bunch of money? Learn how to cast things out of inexpensive silicone caulk and corn starch. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Keysigning Party</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Richard Houser</participant> In this hands-on event, participants will learn how the web of trust model works and perform identity verification with fellow attendees. We will do so in a manner compatible with CAcert.org, so you can use the resulting identify assurance to issue your own free SSL certificates, code signatures, etc. With a little additional work, you can also become an assurer of your own right at Penguicon. We will also exchange OpenPGP keys if you have them, so bring your key fingerprints with you! Participants need to bring at least two forms of ID — at least one of which must be a government issued photo ID showing birthdate. Having your own notebook computer able to output PDFs files greatly simplifies things, too. New users are expected to show up at the start, but returning participants from Penguicon Keysigning events and any CAcert.org assurers may show up one hour in. <duration>2 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Knitting 101</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Kelly Vanderwell</participant> Learn how to use two sticks and a piece of string to make works of art!  A pair of needles and yarn will be provided or you can bring your own so you can learn to make things like dishcloths and scarves. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Soldering and Embedded Programming with All Hands Active</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Get Hands-on with a Penguicon Tradition. All Hands Active members will have kits for sale to solder and program the latest iteration of their Penguicon upgraded badges. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Return of Mary Sue</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Lemay, Ann Leckie, Merrie Haskell</participant> The concept of the Mary Sue is back with the criticisms of Star Wars Episode VII's Rey as an unrealistic hero. How does this critique of female characters impact our perceptions of competent women?  Why do men get unrealistic idealized male characters as heroes as the norm in SFF media, but female characters with the same traits are ridiculed? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Beginning Your Home Music Studio</title>
<topic>DIY, Media</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Smith</participant> Filker Tom Smith talks about how to start your own home music studio. </blurb></event>
<event><title>DIY Electric Car Edition</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Chad Sinke</participant> Come learn about the The Avenger GT-EV an Electric Vehicle build by our featured guest Chad Sinke from SCRATCH.  He'll talk about why he did it, how he did it, and how you can build your own car too!  If you're interested in Electric Vehicles, Engineering, or just awesome DIY projects this is a panel you won't want to miss! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Networking for Systems Administrators</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas</participant> Too many organizations have a tense relationship between the network folks and the sysadmins. Sometimes it degenerates just short of war. But basic networking isn't hard--if it was, network engineers couldn't do it. This talk teaches the essentials, in a way that lets sysadmins troubleshoot network problems on their own. Sysadmins have amazing visibility into the network, once they know how to use it. We'll cover cross-platform tools for viewing and troubleshooting the network, on both Windows and Unix. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Homebrewing</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<blurb><participant>Johnathon A. Campbell</participant> There are many wonderful beverages that can be made at home. This presentation will cover Beer Making, Cider Making, Wine Making and Mead Making with a break down of all the equipment needed to accomplish the end goal. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>12 PM</time>
<event><title>Build Your Own Router</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Steven Ostrowski, Tom Lawrence, Britain Woodman</participant> Yes, you could just go to the store and buy a router, but where is the coolness in that? Making your own out of a spare computer or an inexpensive Raspberry Pi gives you major geek cred points. In today's world, with the FCC asking manufacturers to limit access to router firmware, knowing how to make your own is more important than ever. Our panel will share tips and tricks to help you conquer this and get your merit badge! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Reality and Fiction of Artificial Intelligence</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Leckie, Jason Mars, Lingjia Tang, Jennifer Marsman</participant> Artificial intelligences have been a staple of science fiction forever.  But where does the reality of AI end, and the fiction begin? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Retrogaming</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Angie Rush</participant> Join us for Retro Gaming! Including systems from Atari to Game Cube and (almost) everything in between, join us for four hours of reliving your childhood! Enter our Mario Party 4 Tournament and win a retro system to take home! <duration>5 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Women Making Comics in Detroit</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Erika Wagner, Laura Cascos, Chelsea Liddy, Sharon Vinson, Elizabeth "Biz" Nidjam</participant> The creators of Sidekick Girls and the conchair and planning committee head of ComiqueCon discuss what it's like to be a woman creating comics and the comics community in Southeast Michigan. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Cars Aren't Flying, But They Are Driving Themselves</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Emmy Jackson, Krunal Desai</participant> We're extremely close to having fully autonomous vehicles available for sale, and what does that mean for the average consumer?  We hear a lot about Google and Apple's efforts, but Ford, Volvo, Mercedes, Nissan, Toyota/Lexus and Audi are all in this game up to their elbows as well.  Which of them is likely to get to the market first?  Who are self-driving cars going to be marketed to?  What's the state of the technology?  Is this a technological revolution, or a tempest in a teacup?  And are they going to take over the world and kill us all? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Linux Computer Lab (Unconference)</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>No Presenter</participant> Open Computer lab utilizing the Unconference philosophy of Open Space Technology. Bring your projects to discuss. Bring your discussions to projects. Attendees may also peruse social media, tweet to #Penguicon, browse the whole internet and get a feel for Linux using one of our 20 laptops. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Evoking Emotions, Provoking Readers</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Merrie Haskell, Cindy Spencer Pape, Ken MacGregor, Cathrynne Valente</participant> Creating authentic characters who seem to experience a full range of believable emotions is only half the equation in character-building.  How can we use character emotions to evoke real feelings in our readers? What other tricks are there? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Poly and Kids</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Schwartz, Matt Sweet, Max Issac</participant> An open discussion about the challenges, the joys and the judgement of raising kids in a poly environment. </blurb></event>
<event><title>i3 Vinyl Tshirts</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Yajie Wang</participant> i3's Vinyl cutter and Heat Press (shirt press &amp; Mug Press) is coming to Penguicon's Hackerspace!Transfer from a image to sticker, from a sticker to a awesome decoration in your shirt or mug! i3 will also demonstrate the basic functions in our new software “Sure Cuts A Lot”. It’s straightforward and interesting! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Emulators and Emulation: Emulating a Trip Through Craig's Childhood, One Machine At a Time</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Craig Maloney</participant> Emulating a trip through Craig's childhood, one machine at a time. Desktop computers today don't have any soul. Sure you have your Linux and your Macintosh and your "Windows" but it's all pretty much the same hardware underneath. Why not put those gigahertz to use and emulate the hardware and software of yester-year? Craig Maloney will give a tour of his childhood by showing us how to (legally) run such computers as the Atari 800XL, the Commodore Amiga, PET and C64, the Sinclair ZX series, and even some arcade games. Amaze your friends by running a room-full of 1970s and 1980s technology on more capable hardware. It's a presentation you won't want to miss! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Python</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike Bernson</participant> Python is one of the most used programming languages on the Web, so come and get your feet wet with this tool, then stay for the Python Code Walk-Through that follows </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Heroines of Anime</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Maria Dugan, Cassy Sinke</participant> Join our panelists for a discussion of their favorite anime heroines, from Riza to Major Motoko. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Solar Observing</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>Outside</room>
<blurb><participant>Bob Trembley</participant> ReRoot Pontiac, a newly founded non-profit located in Pontiac, MI would like to share its mission. We are a group of students, scientists,  gardeners and entrepreneurs focused on developing interest in science, technology, engineering and mathematics. To achieve this we are designing and building interactive spaces containing examples of sustainable energies and natural systems to promote experiential learning. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Technology in Education</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Andrew Zimmerman Jones</participant> Technology offers many new possibilities for education, including the flipped classroom and the ability to design more adaptable tests, so that students are assessed on questions appropriate to their ability levels. What are the various ways that technology and computer advancements can improve education? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Walk the Solar System</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Stretched down a long hall of the hotel is a scale-model of the solar system! At the position of the Sun and orbits of the planets, you will find a poster(with a QR code) with more information on that body. </blurb></event>
<time>1 PM</time>
<event><title>Ki Qigong</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Dr. Justin Coven</participant> In Chinese, Qi means “Energy or Air” and gong means “work or refinement”. Put together “Qigong” is the most generic term for working with and refining human energy. Ki is the Japanese pronunciation of Qi. The character Ki is found in both AiKido and ReiKi. Common applications of Qigong are Martial Arts and Healing. In China, Traditional Chinese Medicine, of which Qigong is a part, is a $25 Billion business. Ki Qigong pulls from a breadth of different types of Chinese and Japanese qigong, hypnosis, imagery, and other human energy modalities, as well as from new biological and physics models. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Bringing Sci-Fi into the Everyday: Augmented reality in a Children's Hospital</title>
<topic>Tech, Life</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Christina York</participant> Featured Guest Christina York tells us about one company's mission to put augmented reality (AR) technology to good use, highlighting some inspirational sci-fi moments and then describe how they are taking AR out of the movies and creating moments of wonder and joy for kids in hospital. </blurb></event>
<event><title>A Writer's Life</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Tobias Buckell, Ferrett Steinmetz, Cathrynne Valente</participant> How do you handle the daily mechanics of hammering your magical, sparking, glittering craft into the finished product that could sell. What practical habits foster the creative process on a daily basis and how do you manage the emotional blender that is making words ready for publishing? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Freenet: A Social Approach to Privacy</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael Grube, Steve Dougherty</participant> In this talk, we will introduce Freenet, the anonymous peer-to-peer publication platform. We will talk about the features and benefits that Freenet currently provides, compare to existing tools such as Tor and I2P and discuss Freenet's novel approach to networking. </blurb></event>
<event><title>A Truth Universally Acknowledged: Swift Design Patterns As Jane Austen Heroes</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Anne Cahalan</participant> Have you ever looked at your code and realized that a certain design pattern was charging in like a romantic hero, sweeping away the confusion and bringing order to chaos? Or perhaps you've encountered a pattern that you utterly hated...until it's virtues slowly grew on you as you realized that the alternative was a complete disaster? Let's imagine Ada Lovelace reading Jane Austen, and compare some of my favorite design patterns with some of my favorite Jane Austen heroes (neither knowledge of Swift nor Jane Austen are required). </blurb></event>
<event><title>Finding the Right Social Media</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Kass Lawrence</participant> Finding the right social media platform to build your business is tricky. Should you use Facebook, Youtube, Twitter, Instagram, the list goes on and on. This panel will explore what options that can work for you. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Crocheting 101 DIY</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Shetan Noir</participant> Come learn how to crochet!  Bring your yarn and hooks (or some of your stash to help start out new people!). Everyone is welcome to discuss different techniques and stitches. Come learn some new skills or help to teach others new skills. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Creature Costumes</title>
<topic>Costuming</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Gnora Ford-Lepthien</participant> Learn various techniques to create non-human scifi/fantasy costumes. From scaly to fuzzy, find out how to create a werewolf, lizardman, fishman, insect, and more! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Penguicon Board Meeting</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Steve Gutterman, Randy Bradakis, Matt Arnold, Jer Lance, Gini Judd</participant> You've done the convention, you've met the staff, and you've even socialized with the ConCom.  But what about those *other* Penguicon people?  Those shadowy figures that create the multi-year rules, have their fingers on the money, and cause a ConChair to mysteriously appear every year in a puff of penguin-scented smoke?  Ever wonder what the Penguicon Board of Directors does in their secret sanctum, and where they are taking Penguicon?  Come to the Board of Directors meeting and see! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Agile/Scrum</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Donald Mark Haynes, Douglas Johnson</participant> What does it mean to be Agile?  Is it all marketing and hype or does this represent the future of software development?  We will explore fundamentals of Agile software development and focus primarily on the SCRUM framework.  We will discuss things like the element of Scrum, it’s roles, cadence and traditions, the elements of a good User Story,how to write an Acceptance Criteria, how to estimate User Stories using Scrum-Poker, release planning, a few useful Metrics, and follow-up with a few closing thoughts. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Rathbone vs. Everybody</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate</participant> Avast! Rathbone the Pirate will simultaneously compete against all of you swabs, playing several different games from the age of piracy! (Attention: When a pirate cheats, it is only illegal if the pirate gets caught at it. This has been an advisory of the Caribbean Warning System.) </blurb></event>
<event><title>Q&amp;A With Ann Lemay</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Lemay</participant> Join Guest of Honor Ann Lemay for a Q&amp;A on writing narratives for video games like Bioshock and Mass Effect. </blurb></event>
<event><title>"Pieces of Eight" Live from Penguicon!</title>
<topic>Mayhem</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate, Mitch "Duckman" Peters</participant> This live recording of Rathbone the Pirate's "Pieces of Eight" webcast will give attendees a chance to have their pirate questions answered. Special guest: Mitch Duckman Peters </blurb></event>
<event><title>RPG: Roleplay Podcast Game</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Podcast Suite</room>
<blurb><participant>Jody Raiford</participant> Some of the best improv I've ever been part of has been around a gaming table.  We're going to set up recording gear and then run a short gaming session.  The recording will be edited into a radio play that will be made available online right after the con. We'll be using a system that doesn't require any previous knowledge to play. All you need to bring is your willingness to get into character! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Tom Smith Concert</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Smith</participant> Apparent Nifty Guest In Perpetuity Tom Smith is back, with new songs, a new album (a kids' album! Must be the apocalypse), and the usual assortment of catchy tunes and lousy puns. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Security Principles for Programmers</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Susan Sons</participant> A Senior Systems Analyst from the Center for Applied Cybersecurity Research will present a few basic information security principles and demonstrate how to apply them to programming of any kind.  Make your code less exploitable. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Kitchen Hacks 101</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Emily Tuesday</participant> An incomplete and tangential discussion about tricks to save time, money, and energy in the kitchen. </blurb></event>
<time>2 PM</time>
<event><title>Introduction to Parkour Featuring Phoenix Freerunning Academy</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Jesse Harrison, Anthony Rembisz, Raymond Guzzo</participant> Parkour is a physical movement discipline that focuses on getting from point A to point B in the most efficient way possible, navigating obstacles along the way, most often in urban environments. Phoenix Freerunning Academy is a parkour and freerunning gym in Livonia that teaches the discipline of parkour and the instructors from this gym will be returning to Penguicon to host another Introduction to Parkour workshop in which we will both demonstrate some of our abilities as well as teach you how to jump, how to roll, how to balance and we will go over some of the basic vaults, including safety, speed and kong! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Business Class Networking on a Home Budget</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Lawrence</participant> This presentation on networking on a home budget will cover DDWRT, pFsense and UniFi wireless routers </blurb></event>
<event><title>Rapid Prototyping on the Android with Tcl/Tk</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Clif Flynt</participant> Tcl/Tk applications run on the Android. The AndroWish SDK is a clean way to turn a Tcl script into an Android App. I'll demonstrate making a speech input to-do list in under 100 lines of code. </blurb></event>
<time>3 PM</time>
<event><title>Set-up and Run Your Own Intelligent Personal Assistant</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Jason Mars, Lingjia Tang</participant> Hack of Honor guests Jason Mars and Lingjia Tang will give a hands on seminar on setting up and running your own Intelligent Personal Assistants (IPA) like Apple's Siri, or Sirius, their open-source personal assistant. </blurb></event>
<time>2 PM</time>
<event><title>Understanding &amp; Protecting Your Privacy Online</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Ryan Kather</participant> Everyday it seems more of our daily lives are intertwined with our online identities, and yet it seems that there is ever less privacy online.  Come learn how interested parties are monitoring you online, what drives their motivations, and steps you can take to mitigate your private information exposure. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Pupal Writers Panel</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Haeger, Christian Klaver, Ken MacGregor, Christopher Purrett, Janice Leach</participant> You've written a bit, you've published a bit, now what? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Social Media Entertainers Collide</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Kass Lawrence, Crazy Mark, Dave Phillips, Bob Waltenspiel, Nuri Gocay, Karen Hubbard, Scott (Toaden) Maiale, BluRaven C. Houvener, Trooper Isomorph, Trooper Mindtrick</participant> Entertainers from different aspects of social media (YouTube, Podcasting, Music, Public Television, and others) discuss aspects of working on-line and sharing their experiences. </blurb></event>
<event><title>All Hands Active Embedded Software</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Nick Ristow, Nathan Yost</participant> Our 2016 Charity, All Hands Active, will talk about the development of the Penguicon Uber Badge. They will demonstrate PCB Board Development with open source tools and demonstrate arduino programming from the ground up. Noteworthy addendum! There will be 20 laptops available in the lab. First come, first served. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>So You Want to Get a Degree in Comics?</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Elizabeth "Biz" Nidjam</participant> Have you ever wanted to write an essay on the Marvel universe? How about an honors thesis or a dissertation? This panel discusses the ins and outs of studying comics at the university level and introduces the fundamentals of comics studies. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Introduction to Exoplanet art with the GIMP 1</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Jason Rutherford</participant> Missions like the Kepler telescope have shown our galaxy be home to countless exoplanets, but it is still up to artists to imagine how these planets.  Discover how easy it is for someone with no artistic experience to create beautiful exoplanet images with the open source editor the GIMP. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Queer: Identity, Sexuality and Beyond</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Schwartz, Matt Sweet, Max Issac</participant> Queer means so many thing to so many people: gender identity, orientation, even a political statement of who you are. Let's talk about the range of identities that fall under the queer label. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Soldering and Embedded Programming with All Hands Active</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Get Hands-on with a Penguicon Tradition. All Hands Active members will have kits for sale to solder and program the latest iteration of their Penguicon upgraded badges. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Arkham Horror</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Cory Tebo</participant> A cooperative adventure game themed around H.P Lovecraft's Cthulhu Mythos. It's up to the Investigators to prevent one of the eight Ancient Ones from breaking into our world. During the course of the game, players will upgrade with skills, allies, items, weapons, and spells. It's up to the players to clean out the streets of Arkham by fighting many different types of monsters, but their main goal is to close portals to other dimensions that are opening up around town. With too many portals open the Ancient One awakens and the players only have one last chance to save the world. Defeat the Ancient One in combat! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Authentic Pirate Games</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate</participant> Learn several card games and board games from the late 17th and early 18th centuries. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Ann Leckie Reading</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Leckie</participant> Join Guest of Honor Ann Leckie for a reading and a chance to have your books signed. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Works of Miyazaki</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Maria Dugan, Cassy Sinke, Sal Palland</participant> Whether you're already a fan or new to the works of Japanese animation legend Hayao Miyazaki, this discussion, with examples of his work, will have something for you. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Tor: what is it and is it an onion?</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Portage Auditorium</room>
<blurb><participant>Pat Baker</participant> A general background of TOR, the onion router. Includes discussion on how to install it and some of the options to create your own dark web sites. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Raspberry Pi Hacks</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Callaway, Ruth Suehle</participant> Ruth Suehle and Tom Callaway will talk about the $35 mini-computer, how it works, and give lots of ideas and inspirations on what you can do with it. They are the co-authors of the O'Reilly book "Raspberry Pi Hacks", and generally do all sorts of things with the credit-card sized computer that are fun and warranty voiding. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Vegan Junk Food: Delicious and Not at All Nutritious</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Amy Alice Wright</participant> Think vegans are waifish, pallid folk who munch broccoli all day? Join a Fat Vegan who totally knows what she's talking about and enter the tasty world of naughty vegan treats! We'll sample many yummy chips, cookies, candy, and more until your guard is down and the Vegan Army recruits you. Kidding! We will also talk about hidden animal-based ingredients, sugar processing, and how you can make decadent vegan goodies at home. </blurb></event>
<time>3 PM</time>
<event><title>Writing the Alien</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Tobias Buckell, Ferrett Steinmetz, Ramses Alcaide</participant> The challenge of writing an intelligence unlike our own lies at the heart of much of our best science fiction. How does an author tackle this difficult task? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Character Problems – What's an Author to Do?</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Stacy Bender, Mary Lynn Gibbs, Paul Kemner, Emmy Jackson, Cindy Spencer Pape</participant> A main character needs to start out annoying, boring, or unappealing. (they have to grow from somewhere!) Your readers say 'ugh' and set your book aside. What's an author to do? How do we avoid this? Examples? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Microservices</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Richard Herrell</participant> Presentation based on the books "Building Microservices" by Sam Newman and "Release It! Design and Deploy Production Ready Software" by Michael T. Nygard. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Journalism Today</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>"Ay-hole" Andrew Zelasko, "Junkhead" Joshua Jankiewicz, David Herndon, Erica McClain</participant> Are Independent websites taking over media magazine audiences? Where should new journalists start and how is Traditional Journalism changing?  Join Junkhead Josh Jankiewicz (Hardcore Gaming 101) Ay-hole Andy (blahblahmusic .com) and veteran journalists Erica McClain and Dave Herndon as they share their experiences and tips about Journalism. </blurb></event>
<event><title>LN2 Guest Flavors Ice Cream</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room>Consuite</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Elkins, Phil Salkie</participant> Ice cream flavors celebrating the 2016 guests of honor and featured guests (e.g., Radchai tea ice cream) <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Cosplay Hacks Part 1</title>
<topic>Costuming</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson, John Belden</participant> Do you have a great costume idea but can't find a pattern or the ability to make it? I have some great advice and techniques that will help you get through it all. We will be addressing alteration of existing items or patterns, pattern creation, sewing alternatives, and some clever tricks to help you on your way. Part 1 of 2. </blurb></event>
<event><title>A Panel on Paneling</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Daniel Dugan, Rathbone the Pirate</participant> In this mayhem fueled panel, Daniel Dugan will demonstrate everything that could possibly go wrong during a panel. Expect a few laughs, awkward pauses, loaded questions and general mischief. </blurb></event>
<event><title>AsteroidDay</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Bob Trembley, Krunal Desai</participant> Bob Trembly and Krunal Desai talk all things asteroids, and what we need to know about them. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Make a Cute Penguin Plushie!</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Janet Gocay</participant> Come to this workshop to learn how to hand sew a small plushie penguin from felt. Leave with your own adorable penguin and ideas about how to create your own plushies. No sewing experience required. This is a limited participation event. Sign up in advance at Ops. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Demo Build of the Single-Chip Space Invader Synth</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>Hackerspace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>David Erik Nelson</participant> The Single-Chip Space Invader Synth is a simple knob-controlled sound synthesizer with a straightforward design, low part-count, and high degree of chiptuney awesomeness. Come chat with author David Erik Nelson as he builds one live on stage—and raffles off the working synth at the end! </blurb></event>
<event><title>DIY Electronic Synth Equipment</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>David Erik Nelson</participant> The Single-Chip Space Invader Synth is a simple knob-controlled sound synthesizer with a straightforward design, low part-count, and high degree of chiptuney awesomeness. Come chat with author David Erik Nelson as he builds one live. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Doctor Who</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Join fans of Doctor Who for an open discussion about all things timey-whimey. Birds of a Feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Creating Safer Spaces</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Mark Oshiro, Tanya DePass, Mari Brighe, Scott Kennedy, Sal Palland</participant> How do we define a "safe space" in fandom and at conventions? How can we work to create safer spaces for all attendees at Penguicon and other conventions, and in our lives outside of fandom? Join a discussion with Penguicon staff (including the con chair) and our guests about how the Penguicon commuity can work toward greater safety, diversity and inclusivity to make this a space where all feel welcome. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Best Fighting Scenes in Anime</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Cassy Sinke</participant> Come enjoy a review of some of the most epic fighting scenes in Anime. We'll include sword fighting, gun fighting, and even an over the top food fighting scene! Audience participation will be encouraged and if you're lucky you may win a prize. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>The Found Footage Short Film Format - "Haunt Hunters"</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike Madigan, Matthew Peach</participant> Screening of a series of locally-produced found footage short films called "Haunt Hunters" that deal with an investigative team on the hunt for ghosts, zombies and the supernatural. A total of three films about 10 minutes each. Q and A with creators following screening. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Fun with Mind Reading</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Jennifer Marsman</participant> Using EEG and Azure Machine Learning to perform lie detection. Today, we have the technology to “read minds” (well, EEG waves!).  Using an EPOC headset from Emotiv, I have captured 14 channels of EEG (brain waves) while subjects lied and answered truthfully to a series of questions.  I fed this labelled dataset into Azure Machine Learning to build a classifier which predicts whether a subject is telling the truth or lying.  In this session, I will share my results on this “lie detector” experiment.  I will show my machine learning models, data cleaning process, results, and next steps/resources. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Baking and Breaking Bread</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>David Clipner</participant> "The most exciting thing about making bread is it's similar to making beer." Learn how to make and recognize a great loaf of bread with our Featured Guest and professional baker, David Clipner. </blurb></event>
<time>4 PM</time>
<event><title>Body Painting</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Jeannie Arquette</participant> Come watch a live demonstration of body painting!  Jeannie Arquette and her team from Artifice FX will create a character design just from body paint on a model while you watch! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>How Will Technology Change Society?</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Deb Nicholson, Jason Mars, Lingjia Tang</participant> How we develop our technology may determine the world we will have in the future. Will it be a world of increasing personal freedom, or a totalitarian dystopia? And are we making that decision right now without knowing it? <duration>1 hour</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Finding an Agent</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Merrie Haskell, Tobias Buckell, Ann Leckie, Stacy Bender, Mary Lynn Gibbs</participant> What are the best methods for finding the best agent for you? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Costume Contest Muster</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Crazy Mark, Alex Drummer, Justin Coluzzi, Kevin McLeod</participant> Each year there is a chance for people who love making costumes and cosplay to show off their creations and passion. Entrants should show up for the Muster at least 30 minutes before the contest for judging.  So come down for some fun and maybe enter for a chance to win prizes. Best of Show receives a free badge to Penguicon 2017! Plus, throughout the weekend, N.U.E.T, better known as the Con Scouts will be running around asking people to enter the Hall Favorite Contest. All it takes is allowing N.U.E.T. to take a photo of you in your costume and some basic contact information. Pictures will be posted at the Greeters’ Desk, where every attendee gets one vote for their favorite costume. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Writing Fast and Slow</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Alex Kourvo, Jen Haeger, Jim Leach, Cathrynne Valente</participant> Are you a hack if you write quickly? Are you an amateur if you write slowly? How many books a year should a working writer produce, and how has that expectation changed in today’s publishing climate? How quickly do readers want—or expect—the next book? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Computer Lab (Unconference)</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>No Presenter</participant> Open Computer lab utilizing the Unconference philosophy of Open Space Technology. Bring your projects to discuss. Bring your discussions to projects. Attendees may also peruse social media, tweet to #Penguicon, browse the whole internet and get a feel for Linux using one of our 20 laptops. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Party Planning</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson, Mitchell Bowling</participant> Whether it's a formal dinner or gaming night, how to prepare for, run, and still enjoy your get-together. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Webcomics 101-Characters and Story</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Erika Wagner, Laura Cascos</participant> Erika Wagner and Laura Cascos have seen it all in the Webcomics community! As the creative minds and executors of the wildly popular Webcomic Sidekick Girl for over 9 years, they are masters at the craft. Join these titans for this first of three panels as they break down the webcomic creation process and have some fun doing it! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Tech Behind Asteroid Mining</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Krunal Desai</participant> Krunal Desai, senior avionics engineer at Planetary Resources, the asteroid mining company talks about some of the technologies we use, and the challenges we face in mining asteroids. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Sherlock</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Join fans for an open discussion of the BBC powerhouse Sherlock. Birds of a Feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Python Code Walk-Through</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike Bernson</participant> Follow-up to the Intro to Python, our presenter from the Ann Arbor Python Users Group will take you through some actual code. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Encrypted Backups with Tarsnap</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas</participant> Online backup is incredibly useful, but has many privacy and integrity risks. Tarsnap is an online backup service that only handles your data in encrypted form. It's inexpensive and reliable. Plus you don't need to trust the Tarsnap service--they can't access your backups even if they want to. And Tarsnap's built-in deduplication saves space, letting you store terabytes of backups in mere gigabytes of disk. This talk takes you through using Tarsnap, from backing up a system to customizing and rotating backups, to fully restoring them. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Tastes that Taste Great Together</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Cathy Raymond, Eric S. Raymond</participant> Join Cathy and Eric Raymond for a different kind of chocolate tasting: tastes of dark chocolate combined with other flavors and foods, such as bacon!  Or vanilla!  This tasting will include a talk about foods that were historically combined with chocolate in South America and, later, in Europe. </blurb></event>
<time>5 PM</time>
<event><title>Internet Security for the Lay Geek</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Tony Bemus</participant> Do you sometimes feel like people who advocate security are speaking a foreign language? Would you like some practical advice you can use even if you are not an IT Professional? Then come hear Tony Bemus from the Sunday Morning Linux Review as he explains in layman's terms how to be more secure with your Internet-connected computer. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Costume Contest</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Crazy Mark, Alex Drummer, Justin Coluzzi, Kevin McLeod</participant> Each year there is a chance for people who love making costumes and cosplay to show off their creations and passion. Entrants should show up for the Muster at least 30 minutes before the contest for judging.  So come down for some fun and maybe enter for a chance to win prizes. Best of Show receives a free badge to Penguicon 2017! Plus, throughout the weekend, N.U.E.T, better known as the Con Scouts will be running around asking people to enter the Hall Favorite Contest. All it takes is allowing N.U.E.T. to take a photo of you in your costume and some basic contact information. Pictures will be posted at the Greeters’ Desk, where every attendee gets one vote for their favorite costume. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Star Wars</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Join fans for an open discussion about the franchise, Epidode 7, and the changes the Star Wars universe has seen over the years. Birds of a Feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Grand Circus' Traveling Circus: Intro to Coding</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Chioke Mose-Telesford, Kim Driscoll</participant> We recognize coding can be a bit intimidating. You might have dabbled on the web with some free coding programs, but run into a road-block without the support of an instructor. That's where our Intro to Coding Workshop, lovingly called  “The Traveling Circus,” comes in. This is designed for folks who are curious about coding, but who have little to no experience. You'll walk away with some basic programming foundations in Javascript/HTML/CSS to start learning on your own!  This workshop will also be offered on Sunday! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Forget About Operating System, is the Type of Chip Architecture Still Relevant?</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>William E. Bowen</participant> With the increasing number of single board computers such as the Beaglebone Black, The Chip, Raspberry Pi, Orange Pi, and Banana Pi along with numerous Linux and other alternative operating systems to run on them is it still that important to have an x86 processor in your next computer.  This panel will include an open discussion on the numerous platforms in existence along with the homebrew and open source support for older computer chip sets such as the PowerPC. </blurb></event>
<event><title>ConFusion ConCom Meeting</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>ConFusion ConCom</participant> Join the 2017 ConFusion concom for a sneak peek at what might be in store for next January at out sister con! <duration>2 hours</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Hackforge Demo</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Morris</participant> Windsor Hackforge is a shared space where creative technological minds come together and make things happen. They are bringing a hands-on project to this side of the Detroit River. Watching is free, but attendees who want to build along will be asked for a donation to cover the costs of materials. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Lighter Side of Poly</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Mitch "Duckman" Peters, Jennifer Resibig, Katherine Hatfield Nix</participant> Do you want to talk about the difference between primary and secondary partners, negotiations, and the drama and heartache that comes with polyamorous relationships? Well, then, this panel is not for you! We're here to talk about all the good, fun times you can have in an open relationship, when you love more than one person. We'll laugh, we'll joke, and maybe remind people why they're poly after all! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Surviving a Nuclear Holocaust</title>
<topic>Life, Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>David J. Newland</participant> This presentation will focus on how to survive, and maybe even thrive, after a nuclear event, be it a nuclear plant accident, a "dirty bomb" or a nuclear attack, The presentation will involve practical applications of radiation detection instrumentation, contamination and radiation control measures, why the fear of radiation exposure is overblown, and long term strategies for thriving when others have failed. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Acts of Shameless Self-Promotion</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Dave Klecha, Michael W. Lucas, Jackie Morgan, Steven Saus</participant> What's the best way to get your name forward? </blurb></event>
<time>6 PM</time>
<event><title>Biohacking 101</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Amal Graafstra, Anita Fowler</participant> Have you ever thought about getting an RFID chip or a magnet implanted in your hand so you can interact with computers or even feel electricity? Featured Guests Dangerous Things break down what biohacking is and answer your questions about how it can work for you. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Diversity in Geek Media</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Tanya DePass, Ann Lemay, Lingjia Tang, Mark Oshiro</participant> The push for more diversity has become a regular topic in the world of genre media and games, from calling out instances of white-washing and queer-baiting, to protesting the inevitable and often inexplicable deaths of queer characters and characters of color. It's an exhausting road, but is it actually leading to more diverse and inclusive media? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Comics</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Elizabeth "Biz" Nidjam</participant> We've all grown up around comics, watched tons of movie adaptations of them, and gathered around the television on Saturday mornings to watch cartoons based on them ...right? Well in case you didn't, this panel is for you! Learn about comics media and why it's so great! An intro for the uninitiated! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The 10 Commandments of Networking</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Dave Phillips, Bob Waltenspiel</participant> Networking is the key to moving your career forward. Whether you know it or not, whether you want to admit it or not, others have a huge say in where you go and what you do career wise. The co-founders of IT in the D have created the 10 Commandments of Networking to keep it simple and easy to understand. With more than 2000 hires from their (completely free to attendees) events, they know a little bit about what they're saying. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Unsexy Code</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Susan Sons</participant> For people who write or want to learn to write infrastructure code, and boring but necessary tools of the trade for programmers and sysadmins.  It is not for game programmers or web designers or anybody who makes anything pretty.  We're all about making things work. Birds of a Feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Backyard Brains Demo #2</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Greg Gage</participant> Neuroscientist and engineer Greg Gage will demonstrate the SpikerBox -- a small rig that helps kids understand the electrical impulses that control the nervous system. He's passionate about helping everyone understand (viscerally) how our brains and our neurons work. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Dragons, Demons, and the Laundry</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Christian Klaver, Robert Kroese, Michael Cieslak, Cathrynne Valente</participant> With Urban Fantasy being such an enormous field, how do you keep the sense of wonder in magical spells, fantastic creatures and other mystical phenomenon. Is this required and what is the cost if it's missing? Do characters look differently at magic if it's used to handle mundane tasks and what does this mean to the setting? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Artificial Intelligence in Anime</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Cassy Sinke, Joshua "Ren" Marshall</participant> Come talk about different way Artificial Intelligence has been presented in Anime over the years. This discussion will include classics all the way through modern day. We'll take a look at how AI presented in Anime has changed over the years as well as some ways it has stayed the same. We'll touch on the good, the bad, and the ugly.  Audience participation is strongly encouraged! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Smithee Awards</title>
<topic>After Dark, Media</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Jeanette Quirk, Matthew Quirk, Amy Conlon, Kevin Hogan</participant> The Smith-ka-teers watch bad movies throughout the year and clip the best worst parts to show our audience. 19 "B Movie" categories (Stupidest Looking Monster? Oh yeah. Acting Appropriately Stupid? Got that too) and five clips per category, the audience decides which clip gets to take home the title of best of the worst. Come for some or come for all. It's free, fun and other F adjectives! <duration>3 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>7 PM</time>
<event><title>Introduction to Blues Dancing</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Janea Schimmel, Kent Kovac</participant> Have you always wanted to do partner dancing, but find keeping yourself within a set pattern constraining? Blues dance is an American idiom of partner dance that is freeform with limitless possibilities for creativity, including throwing out the partner bit and going solo. While blues dance gave rise to hip hop dancing, it also survives in modern culture as the awkward high school slow dance. Except real blues dance has more, well, pizzazz and a lot less awkwardness. No need for special shoes or a partner, comes as you are and we’ll help you learn to groove. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Creative Destruction</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Mark Haynes (m), Jennifer Hamilton, Ramses Alcaide</participant> Explore the act of destruction as a creative influence, drawing sources from economic theory, philosophy, theology, cosmology, ecology and technology.  Is the nature of creativity in reality a destructive force? Progress is not necessarily a linear, geometric progression but rather destructive stimulus often precede creativity and explosive growth. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Writing Workshop</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Haeger, Christine Daigle, Stewart Sternberg</participant> Join us for a hands on workshop where writers bring their pens, pencils, notepads, laptops, etc. and participate in numerous writing exercises. Exercises would likely consist of writing prompts playing with different themes, styles, voices, perspectives. A prompt is given, a time limit is set, everyone writes as much as they can or want, and then people are encouraged to read what they've written aloud. This is a chance to  to collaborate with other folks. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Love Hacked? 36 Questions That May Change Your Life</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Edward Fleece</participant> Can there be a formula to the way our feelings grow for each other? Some say a series of 36 questions can create emotional intimacy in a very short period of time, even among strangers. Come and join our experiment to see such claims hold true! Due to the nature of the activity, attendance will be limited.  Participation will depend on demographically matching partner availability.  Couples encouraged if space allows. 18+ only. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>The Different Philosophies of Anime</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Cassy Sinke, BluRaven C. Houvener, Richard Herrell</participant> In this panel we'll have an open discussion with lots of audience participation concerning the different philosophical and ethical questions Anime can bring to light.  This will include discussions about Death Note, FMA (Full Metal Alchemist), GITS (Ghost in the Shell), and more. Bring an open mind and your thinking caps. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Tips for Submitting to Film Festivals</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike Madigan, Matthew Peach</participant> So your short or feature film is finally complete and ready to screen to audiences- now what? Learn the secrets of submitting correctly to film festivals, what film festivals look for in your film, and which film festivals to target/which ones to avoid depending on your project. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Red Hat Ethical Hacking Competition</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Tom Callahan</participant> Red Hat has brought great content to Penguicon once again!  Ethical hacking is testing the IT resources for a good cause and for the betterment of technology. This event will provide an opportunity for both novices and experts to brush up on their skills and compete for prizes. Noteworthy Addendum! There will be 20 laptops available in the lab. First come, first served. <duration>2 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Introduction to Exoplanet art with the GIMP 2</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Jason Rutherford</participant> Missions like the Kepler telescope have shown our galaxy be home to countless exoplanets, but it is still up to artists to imagine how these planets.  Discover how easy it is for someone with no artistic experience to create beautiful exoplanet images with the open source editor the GIMP. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Sexual Safety</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Schwartz, Matt Sweet, Max Issac</participant> Come with all your questions about sex and safety, and we'll talk about how to keep safe and stay healthy! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Learn to Cross-Stitch</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Janet Gocay, Kelly Vanderwell</participant> Come learn the basics of cross-stitch! You will begin stitching using a simple pattern and leave with the skills to continue on your own. All necessary supplies will be provided, and no previous experience is necessary. This is a limited participation event. Sign up in advance at Ops. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Soldering and Embedded Programming with All Hands Active</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Get Hands-on with a Penguicon Tradition. All Hands Active members will have kits for sale to solder and program the latest iteration of their Penguicon upgraded badges. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Cryptozoology and the Paranormal in the Great Lakes</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Shetan Noir</participant> Come learn about and discuss cryptozoology and the paranormal wonders of the Great Lakes region. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Data Analysis Using Python</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Richard Herrell</participant> Learn about Loading, wrangling, visualizing, and plotting data using Python, NumPy, Pandas, and the IPython interactive development and computing environment. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Sirius: The Open Source Intelligent Personal Assistant</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Jason Mars</participant> Hack of Honor guest Professor Jason Mars talks about emerging intelligent web services and Intelligent Personal Assistants, and specifically about Sirius, the open-source personal assistant being developed by him and Professor Lingjia Tang through Clarity Labs at the University of Michigan. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Hamilton the Musical Sing-A-Long</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Talley</participant> Discussion between fans of Hamilton the musical, those who've been to see it, those who want to see it, and those who just love the cast album.  Geek about history and sing along to some of the songs! </blurb></event>
<time>8 PM</time>
<event><title>Literary Filk</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Clif Flynt, Mark Bernstein, Tom Smith</participant> Authors from Peter Beagle to Jerry Pournelle have included bits of song and poetry in their fiction, and and many SFF stories have been set to music.  Join local Filkers as they discuss the hows and wheres of placing songs in fiction and sing some songs from their favorite books. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Geek Girls Are Here to Stay</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Tanya DePass, Ann Lemay, Jen Talley, Lingjia Tang</participant> Every few years it seems there's a rash of discussion, usually shocked, that women create and consume all the things long considered the domain of men: science, technology, science fiction, comics, games and more.  But women have always been there, from the earliest Worldcons to the Save Star Trek campaign, from fan fiction and fanvids, from Ada Lovelace to Shirley Ann Jackson, from Frankenstein to our awesome slate of Guests of Honor.  Will we be stuck having this conversation forever? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Geek Cred: How to Be a Better Geek</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson</participant> Fandom should bring people together, not be used as a cudgel.  How can the geek community become more inclusive? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Polyamory 201</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Susan Sons, Adam Nuwer</participant> So, you've figured out that you should communicate, and you know what jealousy is.  What next?  Come together with those of us who have been at this a while and discuss some more advanced polyamory topics such as introducing new polyfolk into an established poly network, dealing with life changes within the poly network, trying the things we tell newbies not to try, and more. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Speak Your Words</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Jim Leach, Matt Betts, Sean Davis, Jessica Roland</participant> We are all made of stories and sharing them can be powerful and life changing. Come and share our version of an open mic night.  Bring your self-written poetry, personal manifesto, or short-short story. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Webcomics 101-Logistics</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Erika Wagner, Laura Cascos</participant> Did you catch Part 1 (of 3) of the amazing Erika Wagner and Laura Cascos's Webcomics 101 panel? If you did...awesome! If you didn't...off to detention for you! Before you go to detention though, be sure to catch part 2 and learn about logistics and their importance in the Webcomic medium! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Sinclair ZX Computers</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Craig Maloney</participant> Why a machine I never owned is one of my favorite retro computers. In the 1980s Sinclair Radionics / Sinclair Research introduced a series of computers: the ZX80, ZX81, and ZX Spectrum. Originally released in the United Kingdon, they were inexpensive, someone unreliable, and underpowered compared with the competition. Yet Craig spent the last few years collecting for this machine. Why? Should these machines be relegated as mere curiosities of a forgotten age? Has Craig gone completely mental? Come learn the history of the Sinclair machines, their foray into the USA market via Timex, and see why these machines deserve more attention than they received. </blurb></event>
<event><title>How To Actually Relax</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Marie Staver</participant> Relaxing (we propose) may be the most important skill in all of life: It improves health, focus, strength, balance, empathy and happiness; it eases suffering both mental and physical; it's key to winning at physical combat...it is even the single best thing you can do if you're suddenly thrown from a moving vehicle.  But...do you really know how to do it?  Can you mentally find and ease tension in your mind and body?  In this class, Chinese Internal martial artist and all-around movement junkie Marie will teach the how (and why!) of actively, purposefully relaxing. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Pirate Rum History Tastings</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate</participant> Rum is probably one of the first things people think of when they think of pirates. We could give a fancy description of the lecture about the history of rum, but you're really just coming to drink rum-- so let's taste some different rums! 21+ and ID will be required. Sign up at Ops. <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Taste My Pickle</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<blurb><participant>Emily Tuesday</participant> Do you like pickles? Then this is the event for you! A simple tasting of pickled fruits, vegetables, and nuts created by our Food Track Head, along with a discussion of the process of pickling with recipes. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>9 PM</time>
<event><title>Geek Prom</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> It's time for another EPIC Geek Prom, and this years theme is Heroes and Villains. Dress up as your favorite hero or villain and join us for an even bigger party than last year! Bring your Superman or find your Wonder Woman, and get ready to dance the night away until your legs are Thor. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Make a Set of Earrings</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>RainbowRavenX</participant> Come play with wire and beads as we create a pair of earrings!  Whether you have created jewelry before or this is your first time, I will guide you step by step in this creative process. Learn how to string beads, and bend wire to create a unique accessory. While anyone is welcome to attend, a limited number of materials will be provided.  Sign up in advance at Ops. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Erotica in Speculative Fiction</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Ken MacGregor, Jay Maynard, Nicole Castle, Dave Klecha</participant> Birds do it, bees do it, and elves and aliens do it. Our panelists talk about erotica in science fiction and fantasy genre fiction. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Neurable: The Next Evolution of Brain-Computer Interfaces</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Ramses Alcaide</participant> One of the major human developments in the 21st century is the creation of new ways to allow people to interact and immerse with the world around them. Brian-Computer Interface has the potential to bring that interaction to a new level. However, current non-invasive brain technology is extremely limited in capability. Neurable has created the first non-invasive brain-computer interface (BCI) that allows for unprecedented real-time control of physical objects and software applications, creating new ways for people to interact with the world, enabling deeper immersion in augmented reality &amp; virtual reality (AR/VR) environments. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>SF/F Madlibs</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Andrea Johnson, Jackie Morgan, Jen Haeger, Alex Kourvo</participant> Enjoy science fiction, fantasy, and pop culture Mad-libs created by our panelists. Offer up some interesting nouns, adj, verbs and adverbs and be prepared to laugh your head off! </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Art of Negotiating</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Schwartz</participant> From negotiating a scene to negotiating a relationship, come learn some great lessons in the art of negotiation. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Story Roundtabling</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Dynamic story exercise.Start with a simple plot and develop it around the table. Each person is given a chance to tell the next part in turn. Any change can be done by the story teller. Time travel, resurrection, talking cats are all fair play. Each turn is no more than two minutes. We join the story where our heroes are about to land on Saturn F-Ring station in search of whoever stole the E-nabling 3D printed thumb-drive. The smart drive will enable anyone who wears it to break the security codes used by banks and stock markets throughout the solar system. This session will be recorded and posted on YouTube. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Flash Comics!</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Kayla Nelson, BluRaven C. Houvener, Jon David</participant> No we're not talking about the fastest man alive, we're talking about the wild new form of comics that incorporate the technology of today! These comics keep you on the edge of your seat and pull you in even deeper with stunning animations interwoven into the frames! Just when you thought you knew comics! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Everything and Anything with BeagleBone</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Jason Kridner</participant> Explore the high-performance, low-power world with the tiny, affordable, open-source Beagles at Penguicon. Putting Android, Ubuntu and other Linux flavors at your fingertips. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Electrifying Sex: From Quack to Kink</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>(Rabbit) Michael McPeek</participant> What does high voltage and foreplay have in common? What is a TENS unit good for except back pain?  Find out these answers and more with this fun presentation and demonstration. Learn about violet wands, TENS units, and more! Come and try out an electric toy. </blurb></event>
<event><title>20 Years of Pokemon!</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Christina June</participant> This year marks 20 years of Pokemon! In this panel, we will discuss a brief history of Pokemon, our memories with Pokemon, and its impact on the world. Come join the discussion how Pokemon is the very best, like no franchise ever was! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Night Sky Observing</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>Outside</room>
<blurb><participant>Bob Trembley</participant> Join Bob Trembley to observe what the late spring night sky has to offer! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>10 PM</time>
<event><title>Ethical Dating</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Ian Sterrett, Jeremy Myers</participant> A dating, relationships and friendship panel that just happens to talk about people in IT. The title comes from Ethical Hacking and Dating, whether you find people on dating sites, in the outside world or referred to by a family or friend. This panel will talk about basic tips and tricks on how to meet people, network and date. </blurb></event>
<event><title>S&amp;M AMA</title>
<topic></topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Shannon Marshall, Maggie Maiville</participant> Join Shannon and Maggie for an "ask me anything." You have been to "Sex Toys w/ S&amp;M", now get the tough questions answered in a comfortable and safe environment. Submit your questions ahead of time via Twitter at @ShannonsParty and @BrainOfMaggie. Cards will also be available during the panel for confidentially. Mature audience. </blurb></event>
<event><title>So, What's This "Age Play" Thing Anyway ?</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>RainbowRavenX</participant> With adult coloring books on the rise, and as it becomes more acceptable for adults to enjoy traditionally 'kid' things, light is shed on a subculture called "age play." As with every subculture that suddenly finds itself in media spotlight, there are a lot of misconceptions. In this panel and discussion, we will attempt to put stereotypes to rest and remove some of the negative media stigma. Whether this is totally your scene, you know that one guy that does this, or you have no idea, come share your questions and experiences. We will cover the entire spectrum of this fun and interesting subculture (18+ only please). </blurb></event>
<event><title>Polyamory and Kink</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Jillian Hawkins, Darek Hawkins, Ciaran Kingans, Ash Sexton, David Chase</participant> Come and find out how how poly can be different with a D/s dynamic. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Fire Play and Massage</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Dan Eakin</participant> Fire isn't just for warmth anymore.  Come watch some new ways to explore with it. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Mark Reads After Dark</title>
<topic>After Dark</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Mark Oshiro</participant> Come and experience the best (worst) erotica that Chuck Tingle has to offer, read live and (totally unprepared for what's to come) by Mark Oshiro. </blurb></event>
<event><title>DemonLobster.com Presents: History of the Cocktail</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Markwart, Steve Licavoli</participant> The history and spirits nerds behind Sanity Claws Radio's 'Drink of the Week' feature present a journey through history - cocktail history!  From the early muddlings of sugar, water, and bitters, to the first published bar-tending guide in the 1860's, to the birth of the modern mixed drink, our experts will take the audience on a verbal walking tour of their favorite pastime: drinking!  Audience questions are encouraged.  So, if you've ever wanted to know why 'Rum and Coke' exists (and would rather have the answer mixed with comedy than a Google search), this is the place for you! </blurb></event>
<time>11 PM</time>
<event><title>LN2 After Hours II Ice Cream</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room>Consuite</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Elkins, Phil Salkie</participant> Some ice creams / sorbets may be made with alcohol for this event.  Only legal drinking age attendees allowed.  IDs will be checked. </blurb></event>
<day>SUNDAY, May 1</day>
<time>10 AM</time>
<event><title>Engineer's Guide to Self Defense</title>
<topic>Life, Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Derek Newland</participant> Open to everyone!  Come learn or contribute easy ways to add to your self defense skills using simple principles of leverage and movement!  There will be waivers that need to be signed to participate, and everyone is welcome to do so - Minors need parental accompaniment in order to do so. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Tools for Outlines: M.I.C.E., The Three Act Structure</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Paul Kemner, Ericka Kahler, Eric S. Raymond, Michael K. Elliot, Angie Rush</participant> Is your story about Milieu, an Idea, a Character, or an Event? Figure out what sort of story you want to tell, and see which elements are most important, how you might want to structure the story, and how to tell if you've reached the end. </blurb></event>
<event><title>How NTP Works</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Daniel Franke</participant> Those who are unfamiliar with NTP, the Network Time Protocol which keeps your computer's clock in sync with the rest of the world, tend to assume it must be trivial. Those with slightly more familiarity are aware of its reputation for being deeply arcane and full of scary math. Daniel Franke, of the NTPsec project, thinks that both these perceptions are mistaken and that NTP's apparent impenetrability is entirely a consequence of bad pedagogy. In this talk, he aims to fix that. While some background in statistics will make this talk go down a bit more smoothly, a solid grasp of high school algebra should be entirely sufficient for following along. </blurb></event>
<event><title>A Look at LibreOffice Base</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael Rometty</participant> We will take a look at what LibreOffice Base can do by reviewing and talking about selected screen shots from a free video tutorial series about LibreOffice Base.   By then end of the lecture attendees will know whether or not the free and open source software LibreOffice Base is a viable option for their database needs. Presenter is the creator of the LibreOffice Base Video Tutorial series. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Writing Risks</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Leckie, Tobias Buckell, Christian Klaver, Sal Palland</participant> Sometimes it can seem as if marketing departments are only after rehashes of the latest hot thing, at the cost of originality and diversity. Are diverse characters, genre mashups, and unusual structures a benefit to the sales department or a hindrance? How can authors challenge new boundaries and still make the editors, agents and other gatekeepers happy and produce a book with mass appeal? Does this strategy change further into an author's career? Authors talk genre and classification and all the other challenges for this difficult subject. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Linux Computer Lab (Unconference)</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>No Presenter</participant> Open Computer lab utilizing the Unconference philosophy of Open Space Technology. Bring your projects to discuss. Bring your discussions to projects. Attendees may also peruse social media, tweet to #Penguicon, browse the whole internet and get a feel for Linux using one of our 20 laptops. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Self-Publishing 2016</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas, Jen Haeger, Christopher Purrett, Alex Kourvo, Robert Kroese</participant> This panel discusses today's self-publishing options and business models. Our panelists include authors who are both self- and traditionally published, in fiction and nonfiction, including people who are making an income entirely by self-publishing. We'll discuss why we made the choice to self-publish, the pitfalls and lessons learned, and which business choices we've made on our respective self-publishing efforts. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Dangerous Things RFID Implantations</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>Amal Graafstra, Anita Fowler</participant> Yes, we are turning people into cyborgs. Expect a demonstration of really awesome technology that can help you unlock your doors, phone, make electronic payments, contain your medical information, and all kinds of other fun stuff.  Join Dangerous Things as they implants RFIDs into anyone who wants them in a safe and sterile manner! Please stop by the HackerSpace to ask about costs! <duration>4 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Soldering and Embedded Programming with All Hands Active</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Get Hands-on with a Penguicon Tradition. All Hands Active members will have kits for sale to solder and program the latest iteration of their Penguicon upgraded badges. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Gender and Geek Culture</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson, Hannah Davis, John Belden</participant> How do we eliminate the "women aren't real [fill in the blank] sterotype?  Are we doing everything we can to bring more people into the geek fold? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Is It Necessary to Unplug to Unwind?</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Mitchell Bowling</participant> We have all heard the advice about taking time to remove ourselves from our digital devices, but is that really necessary?  Can one utilize technology to relax after a long day of using technology? </blurb></event>
<event><title>DemonLobster.com presents: 8 Player Super Smash Bros for the WiiU</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Jonathon Hickey</participant> Take a load off and smash it up with your fellow Penguinnites in a little 8-player Super Smash Bros! All items will be on and matches will be set to three minute timed battles.The rules are strictly for fun and all are welcome. Positive and friendly attitudes are highly encouraged! <duration>2 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>DIY Electric Car Edition 2</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Chad Sinke</participant> Come learn about the The Avenger GT-EV an Electric Vehicle build by our featured guest Chad Sinke from SCRATCH.  He'll talk about why he did it, how he did it, and how you can build your own car too!  If you're interested in Electric Vehicles, Engineering, or just awesome DIY projects this is a panel you won't want to miss! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Video for Social Media</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott (Toaden) Maiale, Christina Baade, Crazy Mark</participant> Wanting to start a YouTube channel or adding video to your website/social pages?  This panel will provide tips and tricks to help creating videos for new or already established channels. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Everything You Ever Wanted To Know About Traditional Printmaking</title>
<topic>DIY</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>William R. Stolpin</participant> Woodcut, wood engraving, lithograph, etching, aquatint, silkscreen, prints. This presentation will help you understand the difference between these traditional printmaking techniques. You will see examples of each of these processes including the final print and the plate(s) it was printed from. Mr. Stolpin teaches printmaking, and has original prints in many collections including the Detroit Institute of Arts, and the Smithsonian Institution's National Air and Space Museum. Bring only your curiosity. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>11 AM</time>
<event><title>Wearable Computing: Technology You Can Stitch Right In</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech, Costuming</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Christopher Bright</participant> Here we build off the Microprocessor Magic workshop and introduce a specialized version of the Arduino board. The Lilypad is a purpose-built design for the Arduino that is intended to be sewn into a garment or costume. Imagine a keypad sewn right into the sleeve of your jacket. What for? Actuate a glowing turn signal on the back of your riding jacket? Fire up the IR illuminators for your wearable cameras? Or you have a costume and you want the lights and tones to blink and bloop in time with your steps. The modules and connectors are sewn in and in most casdes can be handwashed along with the garment. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Phish Your Employees</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Kristoffer Marshall</participant> 2015 was the year companies started realizing that IT security is no longer a suggestion, but mandatory to stay in business. All of the antivirus, firewalls, IDS, man traps, video cameras, and policies won't protect you from your biggest vulnerability - your employees. Anti-phishing education can be fun, and you can do it too with a little know-how and a cheap server. This is a technical discussion on how to be the bad guy for a minute to demonstrate how real the threat of social engineering is. </blurb></event>
<event><title>IT Road Warrior: The Art of Being Mobile</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Donald Mark Haynes, Douglas Johnson</participant> Explore how to become mobile in your work. This presentation will focus on issues facing the remote IT worker. We will discuss contracts and negotiations, travel (what exactly is the importance of luggage in a global economy), accommodations, some techno-geek concerns and a few standard mobile apps to think about. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Kerbal Space Build off</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Bob Trembley, Daniel Dugan</participant> Build you own rocket - see if you can get it into orbit! Play with Kerbal Space Program yourself, and learn about its amazing potential as both a game and educational space simulator. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>LN2 Sunday Brunch Ice Cream</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room>Consuite</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Elkins, Phil Salkie</participant> Ice cream made with liquid nitrogen, for a Sunday brunch!  Flavors will include orange, coffee, and Captain Crunch or some other sugary breakfast treat. Alternative ingredients available; we can make some non-dairy or sugar-free! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Changing Demographics of Comics Readers</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Chelsea Liddy, Sharon Vinson</participant> Both Marvel and DC have engineered major reboots in the last few years to bring in a new demographic of comics readers.  How has that demographic changed? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Meta-Level Science</title>
<topic>Science</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Dr. Justin Coven</participant> Lessons from Artificial Intelligence, Software Engineering, and Computer Science. Science is a continual and methodical process to match models to data (phenomenon) for utilitarian purposes. Science has the following Elements: Data; Models (e.g. Theories); Properties of Models, including computational characteristics and data matching measures; and Properties of Data, including measures of data to real world mapping. Science has no opinions, has no votes, no laws, no authorities, only naked properties, and measures. Lessons include: Reality, Models, Spaghetti, Measurement, Development, and Issues. Examples include: Entropy, Transformation of Energy, Relativity, and Sub-Quantum Kinetics. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Source Maker Apps</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Richard Houser</participant> The maker movement has been making headlines, in particular the 3D printer space.  Something that is often overlooked is the state of the software.  Many manufacturers ship closed source software, which is against the spirit of the movement.  We'll go through a quick overview of one 3D printer toolchain (FreeCAD, Slic3r, OctoPrint), and discuss possible alternatives at each stage.  Other participants are strongly encouraged to bring a laptop running their maker software of choice (OSS only, please!) to share in a 2-5minute show and tell fashion.  Other maker toolchain applications would be particularly welcome (PCB design/circuit simulation, CNC tooling, laser cutters, etc). </blurb></event>
<event><title>Life-ing Your Game</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC V</room>
<blurb><participant>Craig Hibbard</participant> You've heard of hacking your life, maybe you've heard of gaming your life. But how much attention do you pay to what the game you're already playing is teaching you? Third try is a charm (I hope) for this panel where I will attempt to impart to you some of the things that I've learned from my gaming experiences and things that I think you and your children could learn too. Please join me and see what we can learn together. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Continuing Penguicon Robot Build</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>James Hice, John D. Bell</participant> Come help design and build a robot during the convention. Donations may be accepted depending on the robot design. No skill necessary to help but prior experience would be useful. Useful skills include familiarity with micro-controllers, structural design, costume design, programming, graphic design, and logic! <duration>2 hours and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Penguicon 2017 Planning Meeting</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Kennedy, Daniel Dugan, Nuri Gocay, Cylithria Dubois, Amanda Long-Adams, Amanda Robinson, Miranda Webster, Jessica Roland, Julie, Winningham</participant> Making a successful Penguicon requires at least a year of organizing, planning, and partying.  Do not skip the partying!  Join us for the first planning meeting with the 2017 ConChair, Cylithria DuBois, and her selected Con Committee. If you want to contribute to Penguicon next year, or you just want to see how we make it happen, join us! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Cathrynne Valente Reading</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Cathrynne Valente</participant> Join Guest of Honor Cathrynne Valente for a reading and a chance to have your books signed. </blurb></event>
<event><title>LGBTQ Identities</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Schwartz, Matt Sweet, Max Issac</participant> Let's talk about LGBQT identities </blurb></event>
<time>12 PM</time>
<event><title>Scarf Fighting</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Taqqee Khabir</participant> I love a good scarf; don't you? They are so warm and stylish. There are many different types of neckwear bandannas, shawls, stoles, ascots, boas, and kerchiefs. They are mainly used as fashionable accessories; but they also have a very practical utilitarian use as well. I'm talking about Self-Defense. Come learn to use scarves as a deceptive yet efficient Self-Defense tool. In this seminar you will learn to defend yourself using throws, locks, and binding. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>The Family That Games Together</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Ann Lemay, Scott Kennedy</participant> How does your family game? Do you use games to communicate and relax as a family?  Are games a fun challenge or educational tools, or both? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Self Editing Tools</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Clif Flynt, Sean Davis</participant> Before you expose your precious words to others, you want them to look their best. Clif will discuss a few of the off-the-shelf tools for grammar checking your work with emphasis on checkIt (potential name change), a tool written by a writer for writers to make their prose stronger. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Security Principles for Systems Administrators</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Susan Sons</participant> A Senior Systems Analyst from the Center for Applied Cybersecurity Research will introduce a few principles that form the basis for most information security decisions, and demonstrate how they apply to everyday systems administration as well as system and network architecture decisions.  Make your environment less exploitable. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Continuous Delivery: Fast, Painless Software Deployment</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Mark Henke</participant> Tired of dealing with the pain of manual deployment of your software and configuration changes that can easily go wrong? This session explains how we can eradicate the pain of bringing software to our users. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Star Wars: Bane or Boon?</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Jon David, Ferrett Steinmetz, Michael K. Elliot, Sal Palland</participant> Was the latest Star Wars groundbreaking and subversive? Or was it just merely a rehash of old tropes? Do new characters like Rey, Finn, Po, and Kylo Ren hold up to classic characters such as Luke, Leia, Han and Darth Vader. When does using standard archetypes degrade into rehash and did Star Wars fall into this trap or transcend expectations? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Backcountry Camping</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Clay Dowling</participant> Camping can be something besides a place to park your RV.  Learn about what it takes to go someplace where your phone has no signal. How to eat, how to sleep, how to stay warm and dry.  Where you can go within an easy drive from metro Detroit.  We'll  also discuss some of the reasons why you might want to head into the back country. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Better Filesystems with Btrfs</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Ryan Kather</participant> Better FS, Butter FS, B-Tree FS?  What is it called, and why should you care about a new filesystem for Linux?  Come learn about the advanced features, design, and use of one of Linux's most exciting new features.  We will also cover how it compares to other filesystems, such as ZFS, and other interesting related topics like bcache. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Favorite/Dropped Anime</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Cassy Sinke, BluRaven C. Houvener</participant> Bring your MAL (My Anime List) and discuss with fellow fans what anime is your favorite and why, and which ones you just couldn't keep watching and why. A friendly discussion for all anime geeks to mingle, discuss, and walk away with some new anime to watch! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Print and Play D&amp;D 5th Ed.</title>
<topic>Gaming, Tech, DIY</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Branden Coates, Antoni Williams, Alan Patrick, Nichole Bulmer-Jones</participant> Strange things are afoot in the Moonsea. The factions have called all those willing and able to investigate strange occurrences in the region surrounding Phlan. Dark whispers and unseen terrors lurk in the misty shadows between this world and some place much more sinister. Unveil the horrors before it is too late! Part one of Misty Fortunes and Absent Hearts. Come see a 3D printer demo featuring prints from the D&amp;D Monster Manual, then stay to play through an Adventurers League 5E adventure. Characters will be provided. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Warlords of the 6 Kingdoms</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Nikolas Smart</participant> There can only be one! Take the role of a raucous, power-hungry warlord who’s off to conquer the 6 kingdoms! Select one city at a time, and send a champion to win it using the savory influence of fear, bribes, or pure military strength. If multiple warlords have sent a champion, the one with the highest of the three influences will be victorious. But simply approaching a city won't cut it: hazards and defenses must be navigated, or your champion won't even get close! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Raising Kind and Conscious Kids</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Biz Nidjam, Jen Talley, Ruth Suehle</participant> With so many influences in our kids' lives, how to we give them the tools to make kind and conscious decisions both for themselves and in how they treat and interact with others?  How do we help them to understand and navigate the subtle pressures of the media, their peers, other adults?  How do we help them understand that intent isn't magic, and fair does not always mean equitable? </blurb></event>
<event><title>BSD Operating Systems in 2016</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas</participant> The BSD family of Unix has a been kicking around for almost 40 years now, and have taken different paths than Linux. Come see the last year's developments in BSD land! One of them just might solve your intractable problem. We'll talk about new things from FreeBSD, OpenBSD, plus updates from NetBSD, Dragonfly, and assorted derivatives. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Preserving the Summer</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<blurb><participant>Emily Tuesday</participant> You don't need to be a professional chef or master gardener to preserve fresh produce for the winter! Learn how in this overview about canning, freezing, pickling, storing, and drying in your home kitchen. <duration>00 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<time>1 PM</time>
<event><title>The Most Useful Tropes</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Emmy Jackson, Jackie Morgan, Scott Favre</participant> Cliches in fantasy and science fiction are a big no-no... except when they aren’t. What are the most-used tropes in SFF? Why are they so overused? Are they always bad? Are there ways they can be twisted to say new things about the genre? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Beginning "Scene": Lighting for Small Presentations and Events</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Matt Atkins</participant> A quick overview of the revolutions in presentation lighting since the 80's with a practical focus for DIY performers and presenters. We will touch on the technical standards (DMX-512, Artnet, etc...), have a quick brush with the mechanicals (placement and cabling for venues/locations, power requirements) and cap it off with a overview of the available Open Source and pay lighting control software options and their strengths and weaknesses for this type of work. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Crowd- &amp; Alternatively Funding Your Career</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Tanya DePass, Mark Oshiro, Christina York, Noa Page</participant> Our panelists discuss their experiences using entrepreneurship opportunities like Startup Weekend and Global Startup Battle or crowdfunding platforms like Kickstarter and Patreon, to supplement or make a living, or start a new project. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Comic Jam</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>BluRaven C. Houvener, Crystal Mielcarek, Emily Zelasko</participant> What happens when you take a hand full of comics artists, arm them with paper and sharpies, and prompt them to draw a comic in an unrealistic timespan? No this isn't the riddle of the Sphinx! This is an interactive game that will push these artists to the brink, test their abilities and provide some serious laughs! Bring your sass, clever wit and sense of humor...cause it's you that suggests what they draw! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Software Patents</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Deb Nicholson</participant> Guest of Honor Deb Nicholson, the Community Outreach Director at the Open Invention Network, talks about software patents and shared defensive patent pools. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Sunday Morning Linux Review Live  Broadcast</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Tony Bemus, Mary Tomich, Tom Lawrence</participant> This podcast is produced by 3 local people who also have been associated with Penguicon as speakers over the years. Their podcast recently was added to the player.fm list of Best Linux Podcasts. And as they have done since the beginning, they will do a live recording of their podcast at Penguicon. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Post Capitalism</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Matt Arnold, Edward L. Platt, Kevin O'Brian, Zach Blagg, Dana Nelson (Moderator)</participant> Capitalism worked. The reason it's stalling is that its job is successfully finished: the job of efficient supply. But not demand. Universal employment is no longer needed; but with decreased employment, wages go down; therefore there are too few customers to buy products &amp; services. Basic Income is gaining bipartisan support. Replace means-tested benefits with a monthly payment, distributed in the same amount to every citizen, pegged to productivity to stay ahead of inflation. Stop paying a bureaucracy to determine who needs or deserves social assistance. Income inequality is not just an ethical issue. The existence of a large middle class is the only way to keep the economy going. </blurb></event>
<event><title>PowerPoint Improv</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Charlevoix C</room>
<blurb><participant>Sarah Elkins, Phil Salkie</participant> Volunteer presenters pick a slide deck they’ve never seen before from a list of titles on a variety of topics, and improv a comedic or serious presentation for up to 5 minutes. They don’t have to stick to the slides, as they’re just a prop! Audience members can improv, too, during each Q&amp;A (e.g., ask questions related to this year’s Penguicon theme, artificial intelligence)! As improvisations accumulate, we can build off each others’ topics and Q&amp;A sessions. Come play with us! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Open Linux Computer Lab (Unconference)</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>No Presenter</participant> Open Computer lab utilizing the Unconference philosophy of Open Space Technology. Bring your projects to discuss. Bring your discussions to projects. Attendees may also peruse social media, tweet to #Penguicon, browse the whole internet and get a feel for Linux using one of our 20 laptops. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: What Will Penguicon Look Like in 2020?</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EM IV</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Let's get together to talk about the future of Penguicon. What will it look like in 2020? Your autonomous, electric car drops you off at the convention and you are automatically registered, with payment taken from your Penguicash account. Then what? Does hospitality have a list of you favorite foods that are dropped in by drone? Is a custom costume cut for you based on prior appearances and the movies you attended that year? Let's use our scifi interest to tell the future. Birds of a feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>My Little Pony: Friendship Is Magic</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Christina June, Galen Nelson</participant> Friendship is magic, so come talk with other fans about the MLP show and fandom! </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Media Creators</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Doesn't matter what you create. If you want to to talk about music, movies, comics, writing . . . this is the place to share ideas.  Birds of a Feather events are unmoderated. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Basic Design Criteria for 3D-Printed Firearms</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>EMC IV</room>
<blurb><participant>Zhuang Zi</participant> This talk will teach the basics of engineering structural parts to be fabricated using extruded plastic from a 3D printer nozzle.  Simple design concepts such as tensile strength, Poisson's ratio, and stress risers will be explained and used to demonstrate how to make optimal material, shape, and functional choices.  Particular attention will be paid to the peculiarities of parts made with layers of extruded plastic and destined for the high-stresses imparted on parts destined for use in 3D-printed firearms. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Cosplay Hacks Part 2</title>
<topic>Costuming</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Wendy Carson, John Belden</participant> Do you have a great costume idea but can't find a pattern or the ability to make it? I have some great advice and techniques that will help you get through it all. We will spend more time addressing specific questions and needs of the audience in a hands-on way. Part 2 of 2, attendance of Part 1 is not required. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Prototype Playtest: Quatern and Exquisite Corpse Machine 3</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Andy Malone</participant> Enjoyable diversions or torture devices? You decide! Here’s your chance to playtest two prototype motorized wooden board games. In “Quatern” up to for players compete simultaneously to place a row of four consecutive beads on a constantly rotating board. “Exquisite Corpse Machine 3” is an open-ended game designed to facilitate collaborative art work (and encourage quick creative decisions.) The rules take a few seconds to learn and game play lasts about 5 minutes. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>E-Nable Update</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Daniel Dugan, Maria Dugan</participant> A snapshot of the last 12 months of E-Nable the Future, the 3d-printed arm clearinghouse charity that Penguicon highlighted last year. What has happened between Penguicon 2015 and 2016? What is coming up next? Bring your questions and ideas! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Video Shorts</title>
<topic>Media</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott (Toaden) Maiale, Gabrielle Gamache-Nettles, Dave Kilgore</participant> Come watch some short films by local filmakers, on topics ranging from music videos and comedy to suspense drama and zombie sci-fi!  Dave Kilgore: Percipient (9:35); I got no Talent (2:30); When the Lord Comes to Drown Us All Again (2:35). Gabrielle Gamache-Nettles: Crosscurrent (7:22), Squisher's Atonement (14:00).  Scott (Toaden) Maiale: Win the Cure (3:00), Single White Vlogger (20:00).  Please note some of these contain adult language and situations. <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Intro to Azure Machine Learning: Predict Who Survives the Titanic</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Jennifer Marsman</participant> Interested in doing machine learning in the cloud? In this talk, I will discuss different types of machine learning (clustering, classification, regression, and anomaly detection) supported by Azure Machine Learning. I’ll demonstrate using Azure Machine Learning to build a model which predicts survival of individuals on the Titanic (one of the challenges on the Kaggle website). You’ll leave knowing how to get started and build your own predictive models using Azure Machine Learning. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Let's Eat Weeds!</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Kristoffer Marshall</participant> Do you like eating new things? Maybe you'd like to supplement your diet? What will you eat when SHTF? Did you know that many weeds in the US were introduced from Europe originally as food sources? Many weeds are also high in vitamins and minerals you're not getting from normal store-bought foods. I'd like to introduce you to the wonderful (free) world of weeds! Your backyard is an untapped resource of possibilities! </blurb></event>
<time>2 PM</time>
<event><title>G33K Atho10n 2.0</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>William E. Bowen</participant> Come play an open source or retro game while performing an exercise! See if you can play a platform game with a game controller while squatting, or perform a 1 Arm Row with a band with 1 hand and play a retro shooter game that uses the directional buttons on a gamepad on the other hand. The player with the highest number of reps wins. An awesome way to experience somewhat obscure, yet awesome console and PC games, while burning off some con-calories at the same time. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Accessible UI/UX Design</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Christina York, Scott Favre</participant> One focus of Penguicon has been using technology to make people's lives better. Last year we partnered with Enable to create hands for kids, and now we have a couple of people experienced with software interface design who will discuss how to make software more accessible. Because that Internet-connected computer is no good to you if you can't understand it and work with it. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Mechanics of Magic in Fantasy &amp; SF</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Algonquin D</room>
<blurb><participant>Paul Kemner, Ericka Kahler, Eric S. Raymond, Cathrynne Valente</participant> Does a magical system for a story need rules? Costs, unintended consequences, social factors? What about reliability issues? How can we avoid worn-out tropes. How should magic in an RPG and story differ? Is some of the tech in SF 'magic' and should the same considerations apply? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Teens of the Wasteland</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Baldwin</room>
<blurb><participant>Emmy Jackson, Jon David, Ericka S. Kahler, Janice Leach, Angie Rush</participant> Why do so many contemporary YA novels feature a post-apocalyptic setting with teens on a journey across what remains of civilization? What needs to these books fulfill, and has the wave of their popularity already peaked? If so, what’s next? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Sharing an Oral History: The Art of Verbal Storytelling</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Charlevoix A</room>
<blurb><participant>Jer Lance, Dawn Kuczwara</participant> We've all been there: this absolutely amazing thing happened to you yesterday and you want to share it with your friends and family. You take a deep breath and begin...only to helplessly watch as the story falls directly on its face. Storytelling is an art, and like any art it takes practice, study, and one of those books where you draw Sparky the turtle on the grid then mail it to Pueblo CO. This panel will basically be the turtle grid. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Making Moodle: From Community to Code</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Charlevoix B</room>
<blurb><participant>Matthew G. Switlik</participant> Moodle is an open source learning management system. It is used by tens of thousands of educational institutions from K12 to higher education and by corporations looking for better training tools.  Moodle is supported by a huge international open source community which is growing every year. But how does Moodle (the project) manage itself? Meant mainly for teachers, sys admins, and web developers, this talk will focus on what Moodle is, how it is managed, and how to become a part of the Moodle community. If you use Moodle or are interested in how a large open source project is actually managed, this talk is for you. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Grand Circus' Traveling Circus: Intro to Coding</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant>Chioke Mose-Telesford, Aaron Wolff, Aisha Blake</participant> We recognize coding can be a bit intimidating. You might have dabbled on the web with some free coding programs, but run into a road-block without the support of an instructor. That's where our Intro to Coding Workshop, lovingly called  “The Traveling Circus,” comes in. This is designed for folks who are curious about coding, but who have little to no experience. You'll walk away with some basic programming foundations in Javascript/HTML/CSS to start learning on your own! <duration>1 hour and 50 minutes</duration></blurb></event>
<event><title>Beyond the Binary</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC I</room>
<blurb><participant>Jen Schwartz, Matt Sweet, Max Issac</participant> Let's look into our own personal identities beyond the gender binary. </blurb></event>
<event><title>BoF: Manga 2 Anime</title>
<topic>Anime</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Come talk about some of the best and worst Manga to Anime adaptations.  Which were done well? Which were just torture to watch?  Which were never finished? Why did some turn out amazing and some just flopped? Come discuss this and more with fellow Anime fans! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Furries!</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMV V</room>
<blurb><participant>Gnora Ford-Lepthien</participant> What is being a furry all about? Find out about your fuzzy friends. Anthropomorphic Characters, Art, &amp; Costumes </blurb></event>
<event><title>Hands on Soldering and Embedded Programming with All Hands Active</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Get Hands-on with a Penguicon Tradition. All Hands Active members will have kits for sale to solder and program the latest iteration of their Penguicon upgraded badges. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Conclave 40 Feedback and Announcements</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Anthony Distel</participant> It's the 40th year for the Conclave SF convention in December, and we want to hear from you!  Find out what is going on in Conclave, bring us your ideas and thoughts, and contribute to the growth of the convention.  We hope to see everyone there and expect big things this year with plenty of surprises! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Hakosot</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Mitchell Bowling</participant> "SAVE, YOUR, DIXIE CUPS, 'CAUSE WE'RE GONNA PLAY HAKOSOT! SAVE, YOUR, DIXIE CUPS, 'CAUSE WE'RE GONNA PLAY HAKOSOT!" Grab all your friends, and play this game of singing while passing cups. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Kalidasia Fleet Commander - The Siege of Cadre 4</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Jason Rutherford</participant> The Surakari have invaded Cadre 4 and it is up to a small Heragul fleet to hold the aliens at bay. Come defend Cadre 4(or destroy it!) in this two player asymmetrical game of planetary siege. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Learn To Play 7 Wonders</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> As a leader of one of the 7 great cities of the Ancient World, gather resources, develop commercial routes, affirm your military supremacy, build your city and erect an architectural wonder. This is a card-drafting game. Players receive seven cards from a particular deck, choose one of those cards, then pass the remainder to an adjacent player. Players reveal their cards simultaneously, paying resources if needed or collecting resources or interacting with their neighbors. Each player then chooses another card from the deck they were passed, and the process repeats until players have six cards in play. Who will collect the best combos? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Learn To Play Back To The Future</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Jump into the action of the Back to the Future movies in this spinoff of Chrononauts, an ingenious time travel card game! Play as the descendants of Marty McFly, Biff Tannen, Doc Brown and others, as you travel back to the events depicted in the movies. Your mission is to make sure pivotal events are not changed by other time travelers before time travel itself gets un-invented. Using a unique, patented game mechanism for simulating time travel, Looney Labs now puts you in the driver’s seat of the famous DeLorean! </blurb></event>
<event><title>Learn To Play Dominion</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Richard Houser</participant> The original game that created the deck-building genre. Players start with the same simple deck, and use their cards to buy cards into their collection from the middle of the table. They go through their deck repeatedly to use their new cards to buy even more lucrative cards. Each time you play, a different set of ten cards is available. Can you pick the best blend of cards? </blurb></event>
<event><title>Lords of Waterdeep</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Timothy Brown</participant> Lord's of Waterdeep board game with Skullport expansion. 2-6 player worker placement style game with a D&amp;D theme. Rules are quick to learn but still has depth. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Mahjong</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Anne Zanoni</participant> Ever played mahjong on the computer and wondered how it'd differ in person? Come find out! Most like gin rummy, mahjong is played with tiles instead of cards. This will be the Chinese or British/Hong Kong version, as it is easier to learn. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Order of the Wand</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>David Whitcher</participant> Engage in wizarding combat with tiles and wands. Arrange tiles next to each other, so that when you lay your wand across them, it will touch their magical sigils to cast a spell on your opponent. An unpublished prototype by the designer of Tahiti and Nitro Dice. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Pack 'O Game</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Bob Brodis</participant> A series of easily portable card-based strategy micro card games in a gum-sized tuck box with a variety of mechanics, complexity and theme. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Paint and Take</title>
<topic>Gaming</topic>
<room>Lobby</room>
<blurb><participant>Linda Martelle, Dean Martelle</participant> We will bring ready-to-paint metal and plastic miniatures, at the cost of $6 per figure. This includes paint, help, and figure.  Some free figures may be had till gone-- 1 per day per person. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Simple Python Mobile Web App</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Montcalm</room>
<blurb><participant>Mike Birdsall</participant> Smart phones (or other mobile devices) with digital cameras and web access provide an excellent way to record time and place along with a picture. We'll look at code for some example web applications: a photo food diary with time and location, and a hiking/biking record which can extend to mapping. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Senior Sysadmins Panel</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Windover</room>
<blurb><participant>Michael W. Lucas, Autumn Mahoney</participant> Some say systems administration is a young man's game, and that eventually sysadmins rise into management. They're wrong.  A sysadmin who measures their experience in decades has made mistakes younger sysadmins can't even imagine. This panel lets you learn from their suffering, take advantage of their experience, and laugh at their pain. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Eat Like a Pirate</title>
<topic>Food</topic>
<room></room>
<blurb><participant>Rathbone the Pirate</participant> Cuisine is probably not the first thing people think of when they think of pirates, but the Navy food was so bad that many Navy sailors turned pirate just to escape it. Come learn about common foods eaten aboard ships during the Golden Age of piracy and take home a recipe or two to try. </blurb></event>
<time>3 PM</time>
<event><title>Eryndor Dagorhir</title>
<topic>Action Adventure</topic>
<room>Algonquin A</room>
<blurb><participant>Adrienne Johnson (Kalika)</participant> Dagorhir combines fast-paced full-contact combat simulation with elements of live action role-playing. Get a summary of the rules and pick your weapon!  Several people from the local realm of Eryndor will be on hand to spar and answer questions. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Free/Open Democracy</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Edward L. Platt</participant> Can free and open-source software change the way our society governs itself? Come see demos of consensus-based and democratic decision-making tools like Loomio, Liquid Feedback, and Intertwinkles. We'll also talk about voting theory and alternative governance in SF (Le Guin, Heinlein, etc.) </blurb></event>
<event><title>The 10 Commandments of Job Search</title>
<topic>Life</topic>
<room>EMC II</room>
<blurb><participant>Dave Phillips, Bob Waltenspiel</participant> The 10 Commandments of Job Search (along with the 7 Deadly Sins) was created at the request of attendees of prior sessions in order to best help them find a job. They're directly related to, but not identical at ALL to, the 10 Commandments of Networking. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Farewell to the Hackerspace</title>
<topic>DIY, Tech</topic>
<room>HackerSpace (317)</room>
<blurb><participant>All Hands Active</participant> Say goodbye to your favorite All Hands Active members as the Hackerspace closes up for Penguicon 2016. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Where Did the Heroes Go?</title>
<topic>Literature</topic>
<room>Hamlin</room>
<blurb><participant>Jay Maynard, Eric S. Raymond, Jon Davis, Stewart Sternberg</participant> Science fiction and fantasy were once known for stories with strong, capable heroes and heroines. We take a look at heroes and what's happened to them lately. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Correctness Problem</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Nicolet</room>
<blurb><participant>Sam Boyer</participant> Software is terrible. If you work in software, you know this almost rises to the level of truism. There's a long, strong tradition of prognosticating doom among software folks. This talk is about why software is so awful (spoiler: humans are bad at it), how we software folk cope with that awfulness, and most importantly, the implications that the *particular* nature of the awfulness has for modern and future society. It should be interesting for engineers and non-engineers alike. My hope is that attendees will leave with a stronger sense of what realistic risks are posed by the terribleness of software. </blurb></event>
<event><title>The Trials and Tribulations of the Artist Lifestyle Year 3</title>
<topic>Comics</topic>
<room>Portage</room>
<blurb><participant>BluRaven C. Houvener, Gabrielle Gamache-Nettles</participant> BluRaven C. Houvener and Gabrielle Gamache-Nettles are at it again. The last year has brought these two aspiring artists some great moments...but that's not what you're here for! Kick back and relax and learn what to do, what not to do and how to manage it all when your artistic ventures hand you lemons (and the answer isn't make lemonade!) Like always your faces are guaranteed to be hurting from how much you'll be laughing! </blurb></event>
<time>4 PM</time>
<event><title>Closing Ceremonies</title>
<topic>Penguicon</topic>
<room>Algonquin B/C</room>
<blurb><participant>Scott Kennedy, Daniel Dugan, Nuri Gocay, Cylithria Dubois, Amanda Long-Adams, Amanda Robinson, Miranda Webster, Jessica Roland, Julie Winningham, Ann Lemay, Ann Leckie, Cathrynne Valente, Deb Nicholson, Jason Mars, Lingjia Tang</participant> As we officially shut down another amazing, exciting year for Penguicon, come hear about how it went, and what we've got our eye on for next year. </blurb></event>
<event><title>Last Call for Linux</title>
<topic>Tech</topic>
<room>Computer Lab (EMC III)</room>
<blurb><participant></participant> Last Call for Linux. Catch up with old and new friends as the laptops are boxed up until Penguicon 2017! </blurb></event></events>
